<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pacification touching the doctrinal dissent among our united brethren in London being an answer to Mr. Williams and Mr. Lobb both, who have appealed in one point (collected for an error) to this author, for his determination about it : together with some other more necessary points falling in, as also that case of non-resistance, which hath always been a case of that grand concern to the state, and now more especially, in regard to our loyalty to King William, and association to him, resolved, on that occasion / by Mr. John Humfrey.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16468</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12859783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12859783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pacification touching the doctrinal dissent among our united brethren in London being an answer to Mr. Williams and Mr. Lobb both, who have appealed in one point (collected for an error) to this author, for his determination about it : together with some other more necessary points falling in, as also that case of non-resistance, which hath always been a case of that grand concern to the state, and now more especially, in regard to our loyalty to King William, and association to him, resolved, on that occasion / by Mr. John Humfrey.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716.</term>
               <term>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94662:1"/>
            <p>PACIFICATION Touching the <hi>Doctrinal Diſſent</hi> Among our United Brethren in LONDON. BEING An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> both, who have appealed in one Point (collected for an Error) to this Author, for his Determination about it. TOGETHER With ſome other more neceſſary Points falling in: As alſo that <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> which hath always been a Caſe of that Grand Concern to the State, and now more eſpecially, in regard to our Loyalty to King <hi>William,</hi> and Aſſociation for him, <hi>Reſolved,</hi> on the Occaſion.</p>
            <p>By Mr. JOHN HUMFREY.</p>
            <q>
               <p>They were wont to ſpeak in old time, ſaying, They will ſurely ask counſel at <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſo they ended the matter,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Sam. 20.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94662:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94662:2"/>
            <head>PACIFICATION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART I.</head>
               <p>THERE having been ſo little Reaſon for the Interruption of that Union, which was made between the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt Miniſters in <hi>London,</hi> without diſtinguiſhing Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian and Independent, the Government of both over their particular gathered Congregations being (as the caſe ſtands) co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident as to the main: And our Expectations of ſome more general Meeting of both for Reconciliation, ſuffering hitherto Diſappointment; it does ſeem even neceſſary to me, for ſtirring up the Brethren to this Work, that the Difference between them, which is not <hi>healed</hi> but <hi>ſleeps,</hi> ſhould be awakened, and <hi>muſt</hi> be awakened, and brought again to Agitation, till the matter be compoſed. <hi>Muſt</hi> I ſay, not in regard to the ſetting a few righter in their Judgments whom I think out (which yet is alſo intended,) but in regard to this more general end of compoſing the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt Body. For which Compoſure then, there muſt be now either an Agreement of All in the ſame Points, which can never be, for the Underſtanding of diverſe Men will be diverſe as their Faces are diverſe, and I cannot approve of any Man's go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about a weak and vain obtaining that: Or elſe an Agreement only in Practiſe and Love, leaving every Brother Free to abound in his own Senſe, as to theſe Points wherein we differ, ſo long as they indanger not the Foundation. This is that I count is to be done, to which end, Having printed one Sheet with ſome Animadverſions on certain Exceptions againſt Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s Books, Mr. <hi>W.</hi> thought good to anſwer theſe Exceptions himſelf in another Sheet directed to me; and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath anſwered his Sheet in four or five. There is one Point (as appears there) collected for an Error, wherein they have both appealed to me, and I have ſaid ſomething to it: But having not then by me
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94662:3"/>Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Books, I referred the Matter to the Brethren when they meet, and to his Books with this Adjuſtment, That if that Error upon Examination was not found in them, Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſhould ask his Pardon; if it was, then did Mr. <hi>W.</hi> deſerve rebuke (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he erred as all do in ſome things, but becauſe he denies the Error to be there) and ſhould very honeſtly confeſs it, that ſo all might be made up. By this means one of them ſhall get <hi>Love</hi> in ſuch an ingenuous Acknowledgment, and the other <hi>Victory.</hi> I have ſince been accommodated with Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Books, and have looked into them, and find it harder than I thought, to tell unto whoſe ſhare the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity</hi> muſt fall.</p>
               <p>In the Preface of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to his Book of <hi>Goſpel-Truth,</hi> in the third Leaf are theſe words, <hi>The Goſpel hath another Sanction to the Preceptive part of the Law than the Covenant of Works had. This change of the Sanction ſuppoſeth the Death of Chriſt, and his honouring the Law by his perfect Obedience.</hi> Upon theſe words Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> collects that Mr. <hi>W.</hi> holds, that there is <hi>a Change of the Penal San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Law,</hi> which we count an Error.</p>
               <p>Theſe are Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s words, and lye together in the ſame Page, and as to the Conſtruction thereof, I being appealed unto do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe this. That the Goſpel hath another Sanction than we Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, is a Truth on Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s ſide, and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> will grant it: That there is no Change of the Penal Sanction of the Law, is a Truth on Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s ſide, and Mr. <hi>W.</hi> will grant it. But whether <hi>the Goſpel hath another Sanction to the Preceptive part of the Law,</hi> and, <hi>There is a Change of the Penal Sanction of the Law,</hi> be the ſame, is the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Unto the Deciſion hereof thus much I have ſaid in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Sheets before I examined Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Books, that a <hi>Change of the Sanction,</hi> and <hi>Another Sanction,</hi> is all one. And ſo far I am right, becauſe ſo much is intended by Mr. <hi>W.</hi> as appears by the words conjoyn'd and urg'd by Mr. <hi>Lobb:</hi> But whether a <hi>Change of the Sanction,</hi> or <hi>Another Sanction</hi> (being all one) <hi>to the Preceptive part of the Law,</hi> as taken into the Goſpel in Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Senſe, be <hi>a Change of the Penal Sanction of the Law</hi> in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Senſe, is ſtill the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Before I come to the paſſing Judgment, it will be moſt to Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, in the firſt place, to underſtand and ſtate the Point it ſelf. Some Worthy Divines (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) ſay, All the Law of Innocency is ceaſed, Precept, Promiſe, and Threatning. <hi>Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſante capacitate ſubjecti Lex ceſſat.</hi> Others ſay that all are ſtill in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94662:3"/>force: Himſelf ſaith, the <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Threat</hi> is; but the <hi>Promiſe</hi> only, through our Incapacity, <hi>does ceaſe.</hi> Now let theſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Divines that ſay, the whole ceaſes, explain their Tenent, and let us ſee what they draw from it, and if there be nothing in the Matter explain'd, but what we can approve in ours, let them, in God's name, enjoy their Scheme of Thoughts, and we our own. <hi>God hath aboliſhed the Covenant of Works, by ſubſtituting a new one in room of it,</hi> ſays Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> as Mr. <hi>W.</hi> hath quoted him, <hi>Def. Goſp.</hi> P. 44. Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> does not, muſt not ſay, that none but <hi>Socinians</hi> are of that Opinion. There is ſomething now here accordingly, that Mr. <hi>W.</hi> holds, and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> thinks to be an Error: But what does Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſay upon it? Is there any thing he deduces from thence that is dangerous, or of evil Conſequence, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved? Is there any thing delivered in his <hi>Explication</hi> but what Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> approves, and does himſelf, and his Brethren deliver, and preach, if he preach at all, or preach the Goſpel? If the Deductions he makes from his <hi>Truth,</hi> and the Deductions Mr. <hi>W.</hi> makes from that <hi>Error,</hi> be the ſame Doctrine, and that which is ſound and neceſſary to Salvation, what reaſon is there for all ſuch to be Chid, that cannot bear one with another?</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> that Judicious Divine (of whom Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays ſomewhere, that he learned more of him than any one living) does ſay, that <hi>They who hold that the Law remains the ſame, and that God as Rector by Subſtitution transferring the Puniſhment merited by Tranſgreſſions upon Chriſt, and in conſideration of Satisfaction made by him remits Sin, ſo that here is nothing but a Relaxation or Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it, do Err.</hi> In another place he ſays likewiſe, <hi>To think that the Promiſe, Threat and Obligation of the Law of Works continue under the Goſpel is an Error.</hi> He concludes, that the <hi>Law of Works,</hi> not <hi>Moral Law,</hi> is <hi>abrogated.</hi> This Reſolution I reſt not upon, as ſomething dark and too ſhort, for how ſolidly ſoever he ſpeaks of the <hi>Obligation of the Law,</hi> yet hath he not fully ventured to determined this Point, and I think could not do it. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> therefore tying not himſelf to Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Opinion, is ſingular in his own. The <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Threat</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is of force,</hi> but the <hi>Promiſe</hi> only <hi>ceaſes.</hi> This is his brief State of the Point, and I think it rare ſo piercing a Man ſhould take up with it. Did Chriſt come from Heaven to Earth, to take on him our Nature, and put himſelf under the Law, to obey it perfectly, and ſuffer the Penalty to Redeem us from it; and is this all that Freedom, that Deliverance we have from it, that the Promiſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y part ceaſes?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94662:4"/>What benefit is there in that? We are uncapable to perform the Condition of the Law (ſays he) and therefore the Promiſe is void. But neither what this excellent Man ſays here is true, nor is it the thing which ſhould be ſaid. It is not <hi>the Thing,</hi> becauſe the delivery of us from the Law (which the Scripture ſpeaks of as the Purchaſe of Chriſt) is the freeing us from the Curſe and Condemnation of it. To be freed from the Promiſe, what good (I ſay) is that? And it is not <hi>true,</hi> becauſe the Lord Jeſus, a Man as we are, did perform the Condition, and made the Reward thereby due to him of Debt, or Merit, and accordingly entred into Glory. <hi>The Man Chriſt</hi> (I ſaid in my Sheet) <hi>was obliged to an Obedience of the Moral Law, that he might himſelf have Right,</hi> Jure &amp; merito foederis operum, <hi>to Life Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well then you may ſay, if I be not lead by neither of theſe, what is Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi>'s own Opinion and State of the Point? I anſwer, The ſecond Opinion which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> counts <hi>Extream,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> ſays is an <hi>Error,</hi> I take to be <hi>Truth,</hi> and own, that the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Works,</hi> continues (wholly as to us) in his <hi>Precepts, Promiſe,</hi> and <hi>Threat</hi> unaboliſhed. <hi>Do we make void the Law through Faith? God forbid; yea we eſtabliſh it.</hi> I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly thus explained and ſtated my Judgment. The Moral Law, or Law of Nature, is a Law, or Rule of Life or Manners, <hi>in it ſelf</hi> conſider'd (I count) without the <hi>Sanction,</hi> that is not Eſſential to it. The Duty which it requires (ariſing from God's Nature and Ours) in owing to God, if he had made no Promiſe of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> or threatned no <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> for the breach of it; and God's putting a <hi>Sanction</hi> to it, makes that Law a <hi>Covenant.</hi> Now in a Covenant there are two Parties, and conſequently there is <hi>Our</hi> part, and <hi>God's</hi> part, in this Covenant. On our part the Law I count, being the Law and Covenant of <hi>Nature,</hi> does and muſt continue <hi>unchangeable,</hi> and Man not performing perfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and yet bound to it, is in the Hand of his Judge (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe above the Law) to diſpoſe of him as he pleaſes. Every Sin againſt it (though the leaſt) maketh Puniſhment due (the Threat declares and conſtitutes a <hi>Debitam,</hi> though not <hi>Eventum,</hi>) that is, deſerves it: But as to God's part, the Caſe is alter'd. Here is the buſineſs. We are by this Law or Covenant, through our Sin (we and all the World) in God's hand, lyable to Wrath and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and God as Rector and Judge does ſtand engaged to deal with us according to it: But upon a voluntary and allowed Mediation of his Son, and Satisfaction given in our behalf, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94662:4"/>he might accept, to the fulfilling the Ends of the Law, better than by Man's Puniſhment, he executes not the Law upon him.</p>
               <p>There are two Reaſons upon which (when they meet) a Law-giver who is alſo Rector, may forbear the Puniſhing a Criminal. One is, when the Caſe is Pittiable, and requires Commiſeration: And the other, when his Juſtice and Honour can be ſaved alſo, though he ſpare the Perſon. Such is the Caſe here, If God deal with Man according to this Law, all Mankind muſt Periſh, which is Pittiable indeed; and it pleaſed him in his Wiſdom to find out, and in his Goodneſs to permit and appoint, that the Lord Jeſus his Son ſhould interpoſe ſo as by fulfilling the Law exactly for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and bearing the Puniſhment of it alſo in our ſtead, here is no Diſhonour can be caſt on himſelf, or Law, by his dealing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe on his part with us than the Covenant required. By this means did God pay its due Reſpect to his Law, ſeeing, as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at firſt the Performance of it as the Condition of Life, and when it was broke would have his Son re-honour it and fulfil it, ſo he would not pardon the Sinner in point of Juſtice, without an Hoſtage and Satisfaction. But now amends being made him amply by ſuch a Mediator he diſpenſes with the Penalty, as to us, ſo that the Law here becomes not <hi>Abrogated</hi> nor <hi>Ceaſed,</hi> but properly <hi>Relaxed.</hi> It is not an <hi>Abrogation</hi> or <hi>Ceſſation,</hi> or an <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation</hi> (an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) but (whatever the Skilful Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> ſays otherwiſe) is a <hi>Relaxation</hi> or <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> ſo as we ſhall not be condemned by it. The ſeparating between God's part and our part in this Covenant, never came into Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Mind to ſee this. We are not on our part (I ſay) freed from the Law, that we ſhould no longer obey it, or not be liable to Puniſhment; but we are delivered from it by our Redeemer ſo as to obtain the Mercy, that God will not deal with us, on his part, according to it.</p>
               <p>How then (will you ſay) does or will he deal with us? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by another Law, which by the Merit of that Satisfaction he alſo purchaſed, a Remedying Law, the Law of Grace, the Covenant of Forgiveneſs, the Law of Faith, in oppoſition to the Law of Works. The Lord Jeſus hath redeeemed us, his Poor Loſt Creatures, from the Sentence of the Law, by which every Mortal elſe muſt have periſhed, but he takes the <hi>Redeemed</hi> into his hands, and both the <hi>Remedying Law</hi> and <hi>Law of Nature</hi> into his Law (the <hi>Law of Chriſt</hi>) ſo that they ſhall not be <hi>Lawleſs</hi> for all that. They have the Law ſtill as in the Redeemer's hands, to live by, as well as they can, and as far as <hi>Humane Frailty</hi> will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94662:5"/>permit; but they ſhall be dealt with, in regard to Acceptation, according to the Grace of the Goſpel. The Law then remains in the <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Threat</hi> as a Rule to <hi>Live by,</hi> but not as the Rule we ſhall be <hi>Judged by;</hi> a Rule of <hi>Life,</hi> but not of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> It is by the Law of <hi>Liberty</hi> we ſhall be Judged, ſays St. <hi>James:</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly, <hi>According to my Goſpel.</hi> Bleſſed be God for this Truth.</p>
               <p>What Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> will ſay of this Determination I may know if they write again, but I am not ſollicitous about that. I am methinks ſorry for Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> that he printed his Sheet (when mine alone as a Third Perſon, to let the World know how little they had againſt him, how curious the Difference, what need of bearing with one another, had been enough) becauſe he muſt be forced to agree with me, when he ſhould have differ'd, and is put upon the Defence of a Denial of that which I take to have been advantageous, and the credit of his Books to have owned. It is objected againſt him, that he holds the Penal San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Law of Works to be changed. What if he had owned this for his Opinion, and ſaid it is no Error, but ſtood to it? As Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath his, and I my State of the Point, Mr. <hi>W.</hi> might have his, and we never fall out. Suppoſe then the Point ſtated only with two Diſtinctions:
<list>
                     <item>1. As to the Law, between the <hi>Law it ſelf,</hi> and its <hi>Sanction.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. As to the Subjects of this Law, between the <hi>Believer</hi> and <hi>Unbeliever.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
Let him then ſay, the <hi>Law it ſelf</hi> is <hi>unchangeable,</hi> but its <hi>Sanction</hi> is <hi>changed,</hi> and that change to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as to <hi>Believers</hi> (for he every where ſays, the <hi>Unbeliever</hi> is under <hi>Condemnation:</hi>) And let me ſee who he is will be his Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent? I ſay, let me ſee whether any of our Brethren, out of whoſe Books Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> does bring ſome oppoſite Sayings to Mr. <hi>W.</hi> (and thereby ſhifts himſelf off from being <hi>Accuſer</hi> or <hi>Opponent,</hi> ſo as it is not he, but they, are engaged to make them good) that will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to <hi>Oppoſe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>W.</hi> be <hi>Reſpondent?</hi> I ſuppoſe the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to be, <hi>Whether the Sanction of the Law be changed,</hi> and held affirmatively, being but thus ſtated. This I take to be the very ordinarily preached Doctrine by our moſt Judicious Divines (for to be more exact in <hi>Preaching</hi> may but amuſe and hurt the People,) and Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> does know, and I think Mr. <hi>W.</hi> too, that <hi>trite De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination</hi> I mentioned in my Letter to him, which is co-inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with what is here ſaid. The Law is to be conſidered, <hi>qua Foedas,</hi> and <hi>qua Regula. Qua Regula,</hi> it binds us to perfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: <hi>Qua Foedus,</hi> it binds us to it as the Condition of Life.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94662:5"/>
                  <hi>Qua Regula</hi> then it remains Obligatory: <hi>Qua Foedus</hi> it does not, Chriſt hath freed us from it.</p>
               <p>Let us ſuppoſe this to be Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Opinion, and then bring Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Objection. <hi>There is a Change of the Penal Sanction of the Law of Works.</hi> Very well, he grants it. <hi>The Goſpel doth not denounce Death for the ſame Sins, and every Sin, as the Law doth.</hi> Very true, the one follows undeniably from the other. Let us bring then Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Explanation, Comment, or Confirmation of this Opinion. <hi>Though nothing be abated in the Rule of Sin and Duty, yet Bleſſings are promiſed to lower degrees of Duty, and a continuance in a State of Death with a bar to the Bleſſing, are not threatned againſt every degree of Sin, as the Covenant of Works did. Can any doubt this to be the Grace of the Goſpel-Promiſe? Doth it promiſe Life to all Men, however Vile and Impenitent they be? or, Doth it threaten Damnation, or a continuance of it, on any True, Penitent, Believing, Godly Man, becauſe he is imperfect? This change of the Sanction ſuppoſeth the Death of Chriſt, and his honouring the Law by his perfect Obedience; wherein God hath provided for his own Glory, while he promiſes Life by For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs to imperfect Man, and yet inſiſts on ſome degree of Obedience, to which of his Grace he enableth us.</hi> What can be ſpoken more appoſitely, more judiciouſly, more roundly to the purpoſe, and more ſufficiently, ſuppoſing Mr. <hi>W.</hi> had but held and ſtood to this Opinion? It is all exactly true, according to the Point thus ſtated.</p>
               <p>I cannot blame Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> (though I had a mind to do it) to think that this was indeed Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Opinion, becauſe his Diſcourſe loſes its current upon a contrary Suppoſition. Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſhews himſelf a more piercing Man than I thought upon that account. I will turn therefore to another place, <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> p. 115. <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp <hi>oft tells us, that the Sanction of the Law of Works is removed, and the Curſe gone, as to the Elect: This is true, if he mean that ſinleſs Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is not now the way of Life, and all bellow it ſhall not bind Death upon us, ſo as to hinder our Relief by the Goſpel.</hi> Here Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſhews me in a Letter that Mr. <hi>W.</hi> grants, expreſly, that the Sanction of the Law is removed: <hi>It is true,</hi> that is, he confeſſes it. Very good, all conſonant to himſelf. It is true in this meaning, which he ſets forth juſt in the Senſe (I ſay) the Point is ſtated. By the way let Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> note, that when Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſays, <hi>It is true in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> meaning,</hi> it implies that if it be meant otherwiſe, <hi>It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> true,</hi> which anſwers the Quotation.</p>
               <p>By this it appears how well, throughly well all would have been, if he had maintained, not denied the Charge of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94662:6"/>Hear therefore a little more amply Mr. <hi>George Lawſon</hi> (with whom neither Mr. <hi>W.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> nor I, are to be compared) for a Concluſion. <hi>There is one great Change in reſpect to the Law. Perfect Obedience to it was firſt made the Condition of Life; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that Promiſe of Life upon thoſe ſtrict Terms, and that ſevere Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Death upon Sin were aboliſhed, and Faith was made the only Condition of Life: So that it may be truly ſaid, that the Law of Works is abrogated, but not the Moral Law conſidered by it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would have therefore Mr. <hi>W.</hi> methinks here ask the Brethren to give him his hand in again, or if he thinks good he may take it: If not, let us come to the Queſtion waved hitherto. <hi>Is a Change of the Penal Sanction of the Moral Law,</hi> the ſame as, <hi>The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel hath another Sanction to the Preceptive part of the Law?</hi> For an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering which Queſtion, by the <hi>Sanction of the Law,</hi> I underſtand the Penalty under which the Duty is required, and ſo does Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> becauſe when Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſays <hi>Sanction,</hi> he cites <hi>Penal Sanction,</hi> ſuppoſing, as here ſpoken, nothing elſe by it but the <hi>Penalty.</hi> Now then when Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſays, <hi>The Goſpel hath another Sanction</hi> (or, <hi>a Change of the Sanction</hi>) <hi>to the Preceptive part of the Law,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> accounts he muſt be underſtood to mean, That the Precepts of the Law being taken into the Goſpel, are not required under that Penalty as they were in the Covenant of Works, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon does collect this as his Error. The Collection is Rational, but Mr. <hi>W.</hi> denies this to be his meaning. Every Sin out of doubt does deſerve Death, even in the Believer, and therefore the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Duty of the Law, is required by the Goſpel, under the ſame Penalty, though that Penalty is remitted (being not remedileſs, as under the Law it was) upon the <hi>other</hi> Terms of it. Chriſt's Law comprehends (I have ſaid) the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Remedying Law both.</hi> When the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> therefore remaineth, it muſt make the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> due; but the <hi>Pardoning Law</hi> being conjunct with it, makes the <hi>Impunity</hi> due alſo: <hi>In primo inſtanti,</hi> the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>in ſecundo,</hi> Impunity.</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary therefore, I judge, for Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to explain his Term <hi>Sanction,</hi> and try if he can make his words ſo intelligible, as one may ſay he gave no occaſion of Mis-conſtruction: But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this <hi>Phraſe</hi> of his (as I call it in Mr. <hi>Lobbs</hi> Sheets) and much more by that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> hath added from another place <hi>[The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel doth not denounce Death for the ſame, and every Sin, as</hi> Adam<hi>'s Law did]</hi> there is occaſion given to Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> to believe him herein in an Error (if it be one, and the contrary be not,) and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94662:6"/>rationally to do ſo, I muſt, in my Judgment on the caſe, ſo far excuſe Mr. <hi>Lobb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us conſider again, The words of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> may be conſtrued, either with Application of his Readers Thoughts to the Law alone, or to the Goſpel alone, or to the Law and Goſpel both together. If the Readers Thoughts be applied to the Law alone, then <hi>Another Sanction</hi> being the ſame with a <hi>Change of the Sanction,</hi> and that upon Chriſt's Satisfaction too, he muſt needs underſtand the meaning to be, that the Penal Sanction of the Law is by the Goſpel, or by Chriſt's Death and Obedience, made void; for the ſame Law cannot have two Sanctions, and if its own be changed, it is aboliſhed. If the Readers Thoughts be applied to the Goſpel alone, they muſt recur, for there is no change of Sanction que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable as to that. If his Reader conſtrue him with Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Thoughts to Law and Goſpel both together, then may the meaning indeed be underſtood, that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> Sanction is changed from that which was the <hi>Law</hi> Sanction, ſo as to be <hi>another</hi> and not the ſame, without making void one or the other, which yet is a perplext Conception. Now of theſe three Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of a Man's Thoughts to the words (if one did not know that the laſt was the Author's meaning becauſe he ſays ſo) the firſt Application I think likeſt to fall into the Thoughts of another Man as well as Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s, rather than either of the other. So far is he farther to be excuſed.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, when I come to look into Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Books, and ſee with my Eyes what he hath ſaid, I may excuſe Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> in a miſtake of Judgment (if he do miſtake,) but do not, till far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scrutiny, clear him from wronging Mr. <hi>W.</hi> I will turn to his laſt Book firſt, <hi>Man made Righteous,</hi> p. 100. <hi>There is hardly a Truth more plain in the Word of God, than that the Wrath of God abides still upon Unbelievers, notwithſtanding Chriſt's Death.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> ſays, he holds the Penal Sanction of the Law abrogated, and how does this place ſtare in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Face? I will turn next to his middle Book, <hi>Defence of Goſpel Truth,</hi> p. 2. <hi>That Men while they reject the Goſpel, are not at all under the Curſe of the Law, I abhor.</hi> How any ſhould be under the Curſe of the Law, and the Penal Sanction of it be not of Force, I never yet had one thought. Let us look then laſt into his firſt Book from whence the Exception was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> p. 5. <hi>That the Elect, while Dead in Sin and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, are Children of Wrath, and condemned by the Law, I affirm.</hi> Again, p. 107. <hi>The Goſpel denounceth and declareth all condemned till
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94662:7"/>they believe. It declares they are ſo, and denounceth they ſhall be ſo.</hi> John 3.36. <hi>He that believeth not on the Son, ſhall not ſee Life, but the Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> And v. 18. <hi>He that believeth not, is condemned already. Here is the caſe of all men by the Fall, they are condemned and under Wrath: Here is the way of Relief, a Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on, and they that believe their Condemnation is reverſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe places at the reading moved me much, and made me write to Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> but I found him aware of ſuch Paſſages, and not moved, anſwering that for all theſe words, Mr. <hi>W.</hi> meant them only of the Goſpel Denunciation. Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Opinion he accounts was, that Chriſt by his Death hath taken away the Curſe of the Law; and the Curſe the Unbeliever is under, is only that of the Goſpel, <hi>He that believeth not ſhall be Damned.</hi> To this purpoſe may be obſerved thoſe picked Terms of <hi>Governing Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Governing Grace,</hi> which Mr. <hi>W.</hi> uſes as equivalent to the two Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments of Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> (the <hi>Creator</hi>'s Government, and the <hi>Redeemer's</hi> Government) which muſt be ſuppoſed to have their two <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>New</hi> vacating the <hi>Old.</hi> As alſo thoſe Arguments Mr. <hi>W.</hi> offers to prove a new Law, that do notable fit a Judgment ſo poſſeſt: <hi>What kind of Government can we aſſign to Chriſt</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if there be no Sanction to his Law?</hi> But if he hold the Sanction of the <hi>Old</hi> Law (as taken into Chriſt's) to ſtand good, I pray why ſuch a Neceſſity of it to the <hi>New.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs the words of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> as I have quoted them, are ſo expreſs, for all Men by the Fall to be under the Curſe (which does imply the Law therefore to be of force) that I cannot give Judgment upon any ſuch bare Reaſoning. Let us therefore ſee another place Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> points me to, <hi>Defence of Goſpel Truth,</hi> p. 23. Adam's <hi>Law muſt be altered by the Law-giver to admit of Satisfaction.</hi> Here, ſays Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> is plain proof of Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s holding the Law changed: But (though the word <hi>altered</hi> be unskilfully ſaid, and he ſhould ſay <hi>relaxed</hi>) that which follows in three lines after, to wit, [<hi>The Sentence that condemned</hi> Adam, <hi>ſeizes on all Men as ſoon as they have being, there needs no other.</hi>] does again turn the Scale for Mr. <hi>W.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Truth is, the words I am to judge of between theſe two Brethren, are in Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s firſt Book, and it is that alone muſt ſhew what was his mind then. The Paſſages for him I have mentioned, are not ſo poſitively fixt in that Book, as in the two other, after he was warned. And there are two places not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> but obſerved by me in reading the Book
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94662:7"/>afreſh quite over, that do put me to a ſtand. One is p. 221. where he hath words to this ſenſe, <hi>We are not to preach the Sanction of the Law of Innocency, but may preſs the Goſpel Sanction.</hi> The other is in the expreſs words, <hi>Is it the Grace of God to leave his Precepts without any Sanction, when he removed the Curſe of the Law?</hi> Here is the Curſe of the Law, that is, the <hi>Penal Sanction</hi> removed, that is, <hi>changed,</hi> and another brought into its room, as being that (it is like he meant) which lies on all till they believe. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing goes before or after to alieviate this ſenſe, P. 242.</p>
               <p>I muſt needs ſay here therefore, that I was ſorry to ſee this place, becauſe I had come to a Judgment and finiſhed my Sheets, and was brought to this paſs within my ſelf. Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> (I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned) does verily believe that Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Opinion was as he notifies it to be: Mr. <hi>W.</hi> that knows what his own mind was, better than any, complains that he miſtakes, and wrongs him. On one ſide I accounted, here is <hi>Confidence,</hi> but on the other <hi>Knowledge.</hi> I had paſſed therefore this Judgment, that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> was to be <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Acquitted.</hi> There is <hi>Obſcurity</hi> not <hi>Error</hi> I had thought in the words of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> there is <hi>Miſtake</hi> not <hi>Malice</hi> in the Collection of <hi>Mr. Lobb.</hi> But now I cannot (I muſt confeſs) in Point of Conſcience let this go. I cannot ſay there is <hi>Miſtake</hi> herein, but rather <hi>Sagacity</hi> in <hi>Mr. Lobb,</hi> and I cannot ſay there is no Error of <hi>Mr. W.</hi> herein, but rather that he was one then not come to any Conſiſtency about the Point, and that it is beſt for him to be in Suſpenſe ſtill, ſeeing that which we three ſuppoſe to be the <hi>Error,</hi> ſome others more weighty than we take to be <hi>Truth. If the Moral Law</hi> (ſaid ſuch a one) <hi>ſhould be in force as it was to</hi> Adam, <hi>no Man upon one Act of Diſobedience could be ſaved: Therefore that manner of strict Obligation ceaſeth unto ſinful Man for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being ſo, that, what <hi>Mr. W</hi>'s Opinion was at his firſt Writing, I am not ſure; inſomuch as I can bring in no <hi>Billa vera,</hi> but an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> in my laſt Verdict to the Brethren, that are ſome time to meet about it: And that it is like his Opinion was not then ſo digeſted as that himſelf can tell it: Nay, that it is no matter, or very little matter, whether his Opinion was ſo or otherwiſe, ſeeing the Opinion <hi>Pro</hi> or <hi>Con</hi> may be good enough, at leaſt inoffenſive either of them, if but ſtated well: Nay yet, that it may be peradventure in other Differences between our Brethren, no otherwiſe than ſo as it is in this, I muſt come to that Concluſion at laſt, which I came to long ſince, and ſtand to it, that it is not upon a Union in Opinion, or upon certain Theſes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94662:8"/>drawn up into ſuch a Latitude of Words as all may ſubſcribe, but upon a Union in forbearing and bearing with one another in all things but what is of neceſſity to Salvation, that our Concord muſt be re-eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>PART II.</head>
               <p>I Have done here with the Arbitration which I count <hi>Mr. W.</hi> and <hi>Mr. Lobb</hi> appointed me, that is, as to this particular mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and as for any other Points between them, they are not my Province: Only ſo far as the <hi>Middle Doctrine of Juſtification,</hi> which I maintain is concerned, I cannot but take notice how one word, and that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, uſed but once in one place, is the ground almoſt of all their Diſſention. It is the word <hi>Surety,</hi> Heb. 7.22. This word hath been ſo ſtrained, or rather groſly taken, not only by the <hi>Antinomian</hi> but our Divines ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, as if Chriſt were ſuch a Surety for us in the Covenant of Works, as bound with us in the ſame Bond (ſo coarſe is their Speech,) inſomuch as when he performed the Duty, and ſuffered the Penalty in our behalf, they reckon it done in our Perſons, ſo that God looks on the Believer (in Law ſenſe) as having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly obeyed and ſuffered in his Surety, and conſequently that he receiving this Righteouſneſs (or making it his) by Faith, does ſtand juſtified in that Righteouſneſs of Chriſt by the Law of Works. If Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> or any Brother, (it is all alike who they be) hath uſed words to this Senſe, they muſt be rectified. Mr. <hi>W.</hi> is not to come to them, but they to Mr. <hi>W. They do heinouſly err</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter) and ſubvert the Goſpel, who ſays that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is ſo imputed to us, as that God reputeth Chriſt to have been perfectly Holy, and ſuffered, though not in our Natural yet in the Legal or Civil Perſon of the Sinner, or Believer, as their strict and proper Repreſenter, and ſo to have our ſelves fulfilled all Righteouſneſs in him, or by him,</hi> and thereby be Juſtified. There are more words by way of Aggravation which I fill up with <hi>[and thereby be Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied]</hi> becauſe they tend only to ſhew what the allowing ſo much at the beginning does draw after it.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine I have ſaid is coarſe, I add, and grounded on a Miſtake, which I have inculcated in my Book of <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94662:8"/>Divines indeed ordinarily, Papiſts and Proteſtants, ſuppoſing that it is by the <hi>Law,</hi> the Law of <hi>Works,</hi> that we ſhall be <hi>Judged,</hi> do fall out, and muſt fall out one <hi>againſt,</hi> and one <hi>with</hi> another: But let them reflect, and underſtand aright, that it is not the Law of <hi>Works,</hi> but the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> or Law of <hi>Faith,</hi> not the <hi>Law</hi> but the <hi>Goſpel (Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>James</hi> 2.12. before noted) is and ſhall be the Rule of <hi>Judgment</hi> (when the Law is indeed the Rule of <hi>Living,</hi>) they muſt end the Quarrel between moſt of them. Upon this<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hence</hi> Contarenus, <hi>though a</hi> Papiſt <hi>and a</hi> Cardinal, <hi>who defines alſo</hi> Juſtificari <hi>to be</hi> juſtum fieri, &amp; propterea ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum haberi, <hi>hath yet theſe words.</hi> Ego prorſus exiſtimo piè &amp; Chriſtianè dici, quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beamus niti juſtitia Chriſti no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis donata, non autem gratia nobis inhaerente. Haec enim ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia noſtra eſt inchoata &amp; imperfecta, quae tueri nos non poteſt quin in multis offenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Idcirco in conſpectu Dei non poſſumus ob hanc juſtitiam noſtram haberi juſti &amp; boni: Sed juſtitia Chriſti nobis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata eſt perfecta quae omnino placet oculis Dei. Haec ergo ſola certa &amp; ſtabili nitendum eſt, &amp; ob eam ſolam credere nos juſtificari coram Deo, id eſt juſtos haberi, &amp; dici juſtos. <hi>Cont. de Juſtificatione.</hi>
                  </note> account, when the Proteſtant judges that we muſt have a Righteouſneſs that anſwers the Law (as his,) or elſe he cannot at all be juſtified, he does make Chriſt ſuch a <hi>Surety,</hi> and deviſe ſuch a <hi>Commutation of Perſons</hi> as ſuits to that Conception: But he that is clear, as to the Rule by which we ſhall be judged, will be contented with ſuch a <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> and <hi>Commutation</hi> only, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> (I was upon ſaying as Mr. <hi>W.</hi>) does allow him.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Chriſt's Suretiſhip</hi> in the firſt place, I do not fancy ſo much to be made of it even as Mr. <hi>W.</hi> does. That he was a Surety on God's part, and then on our part— and I know not what. The true and faithful God I hope has no need of any Surety on his part to make <hi>His</hi> good, I count that but idle he ſays to excuſe it: And if Chriſt was a ſtrict proper (in humane ſenſe proper) Surety of the new Covenant on our part to make <hi>Ours</hi> good, then muſt all of us be ſaved, becauſe the Goſpel Covenant (I hold) is Univerſal, and not made with the Elect only. That which I conceive then, as to Chriſt's Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip, is, that he was to do, and did, all that was to be done for Satisfaction to God in our behalf, for procuring the Goſpel-Covenant for the loſt World. This I apprehend to be the main of the buſineſs. <hi>There is one Mediator</hi> (which is the common Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation of the ſame import as Surety) <hi>between God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a Ranſome for all to be teſtified in due time.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.5, 6. Chriſt was a <hi>Surety,</hi> but a Surety in the Scripture Senſe, not in an Arbitrary Senſe. Chriſt was a Surety,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94662:9"/>not in an <hi>Antinomian</hi> Senſe, but in a Senſe which muſt be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to every thing elſe that is ſaid of him in Scripture. This is ſafe, and this is true, and here I will ſtand by Mr. <hi>W.</hi> But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt's <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> is to be made commenſurate with his <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> to make good his, or any others Notion of it, I queſtion. It is no where ſaid we have a <hi>Surety</hi> (though a <hi>High Prieſt</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſor</hi>) now in Heaven.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Commutation</hi> in the next place then of <hi>Perſons,</hi> I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſuch a one accordingly, as is neceſſary to the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration</hi> of our Redemption, but I underſtand none ſo as to go into the <hi>Application.</hi> Chriſt took on him our Fleſh, made Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in our ſtead, and procured an Act of Grace or Pardon for all: But there is no <hi>Commutation</hi> I know as to particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Point of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> If Chriſt made an exchange of his Righteouſneſs with <hi>Peter</hi> for his Sins, any otherwiſe than as to the Impetration of Pardon on condition that concerns all alike, then Chriſt's Righteouſneſs muſt now be <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> could never have it. In Chriſt's uniting <hi>himſelf to us,</hi> by his taking our Nature, Obeying, Suffering, ſatisfying God's Juſtice, I acknowledge a <hi>Commutation,</hi> even ſuch, to wit, that our Sins were ſo imputed to him, as that he <hi>died for them,</hi> and <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> (underſtanding the Phraſes aright) and his Righteouſneſs ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, as to be the <hi>Cauſe</hi> that upon our believing we enjoy the Benefit: But in Chriſt's uniting <hi>us to him,</hi> by giving his Spirit to work in us that Condition whereby we have our Right to the Benefit, there is nothing done by him in <hi>our ſtead,</hi> nothing by us in <hi>his,</hi> no new, no other, no father Imputation. The Fruit of his Purchaſe (Pardon and Salvation by a Law of Grace) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>formaliter</hi> his, and if that the communicates to us be not his, how is there a Commutation? Of this Sacrifice and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs it ſelf we are uncapable: Of the Effect or Fruits Chriſt is uncapable. What he hath not, he cannot communicate; what he hath, we cannot receive. It is true, he hath receive <hi>poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conferendi,</hi> and in that reſpect, <hi>eminenter,</hi> may be ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>for us</hi> his own Benefits; but <hi>for us</hi> then muſt be only <hi>bono noſtro,</hi> if it were <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> our ſelves could not have them. The Puniſhment we deſerved Chriſt bare <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> therefore we are not to bear it: The Benefits Chriſt purchaſed we have, therefore <hi>loco noſtro</hi> he could not receive them. There is, there can be, no Subſtitution of Perſon in our partaking the Benefits purchaſed, as there was, there muſt be, in the purchaſing them for us.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94662:9"/>There is a Chapter on this Head in my Book, called, <hi>Peaceable Diſquiſitions,</hi> I refer thither for farther Explication.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> I believe (ſpeaking ſtrictly) that Chriſt was no Surety of the Covenant of <hi>Works,</hi> ſo as to enter into the ſame Bond <hi>before</hi> or <hi>after</hi> (it were but trifling to make a Diſpute of <hi>that</hi>) it was forfeited: And that his Reaſons for it are good, his fourth eſpecially, as to the ill Conſequences following upon it. <hi>Againſt</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> I apprehend Chriſt to be no Surety neither, of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of <hi>Grace</hi> in a ſtrict proper Senſe (as I ſay alſo in my Sheet) becauſe the buſineſs of this Suretiſhip I ſaid now, does lye mainly in obtaining for us this Covenant (as <hi>Moſes</hi> dealt in his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,) and not in the undertaking on God's part (which needs not) and on our part, that it ſhould be kept. In this ſenſe do I underſtand the Prophet, when God ſays, he will give Chriſt <hi>for a Covenant of the People,</hi> that is, to <hi>mediate</hi> this Covenant, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it. The word <hi>Surety,</hi> I ſay again, muſt be taken in ſuch a Senſe (and not any other) which agrees with every thing elſe ſaid of Chriſt in the Scripture, or with the whole Doctrine of the Goſpel beſides: And that Doctrine is falſe (I count) which confines the Goſpel-Covenant to the Elect. <hi>Not that he undertook that all he mediated for, ſhould do all that is their Duty,</hi> ſays the throughly Underſtanding Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> on the place.</p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>W.</hi> I will take leave to ſay, he is to me a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Man, eſpecially as to his Talent, Elocution; which yet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs his Judgment alſo be Good, Staid and Unpaſſionate, as it appears, may prove to him a Temptation. There is nothing I diſtruſt him ſo much in, as in his Diſtinctions, which I cannot but ſuſpect ſometimes (through his Facility of words,) to be made rather in diverſe Expreſſions, than in the reality of the things he would diſtinguiſh. I am afraid leaſt he ſhould hereby come to yield more in our main Cauſe, than we can again recover. This appears more particularly in theſe two Points, wherein I am more particularly concerned, the <hi>Conditionality</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the Buſineſs of <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to be known and acknowledged, there are ſeveral places in the Old Teſtament, which ſpeak of God's Circumciſing the Heart, giving a new one, putting his Fear into it, ſo as they that have this Promiſe fulfilled to them, ſhall enter into Covenant with God in Sincerity, and never again depart from him: Upon which account it is called an <hi>Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> and a <hi>ſecond Covenant</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94662:10"/>in Oppoſition to the <hi>first</hi> that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> brake, as it is in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> In theſe places then we have a Promiſe (for they are all I ſuppoſe in the account of moſt one and the ſame Promiſe) which is an Abſolute Promiſe, that is, to give that which hath no Condition required of us for the obtaining it, the firſt Grace, the new Heart, Faith and Repentance, in order to our Salvation. Now the Promiſe being Abſolute, and called the Covenant, <hi>[This is my Covenant I will make with the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord: I will put my Laws into their Minds, and write them in their Hearts: And I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a People,]</hi> the <hi>Antinomian</hi> does apprehend it to be the Covenant of Grace, and that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace therefore is not Conditional, for there is no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in this Promiſe, and if that we call the Condition, is on God's part given, and not required as a Condition to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed on our parts, the Covenant is without Condition.</p>
               <p>Here now the <hi>Orthodox Calviniſt,</hi> who is neither <hi>Arminian</hi> or <hi>Antinomian,</hi> are of two ſorts, one whoſe Genius carries them ſo much againſt <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> that they come as near as they can to the <hi>Antinomian:</hi> And the other whoſe Genius leads them ſo far from <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> that they come as near as they can to the <hi>Arminian;</hi> but either of them carefully avoiding the Danger of both Errors. Under the firſt ſort I muſt rank Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mather,</hi> and ſuch as will ſay here (with Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi>) that this Promiſe is <hi>part</hi> of the Covenant of Grace (not the <hi>whole</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,) and that this Promiſe of Faith, or the firſt Grace, being part of the Covenant-Bleſſings, and the Fruit of Chriſt's Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe for the Elect, the Covenant in this reſpect is without any <hi>Antecedent</hi> Condition: But the firſt Grace being given in order to obtain farther Bleſſings, that firſt Grace (I ſuppoſe in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) is a <hi>Conſequent</hi> Condition (in regard to the Connexion between them) to thoſe Benefits, and ſo ſave they themſelves from <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi> Under the <hi>Latter</hi> ſort, I had thought I might have ranked Mr. <hi>W.</hi> with my ſelf, but I will name one more worthy than we, for his moſt acute and ſtrong parts, Mr. <hi>Woodbridge,</hi> who does deny this Promiſe to be part of the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> made with Fallen Man: But that it is either an indefinite Promiſe, which God will make good on whom he pleaſes in their uſe of means, or a Promiſe in regard to the <hi>Elect,</hi> not made to <hi>them,</hi> but made to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Covenant of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (if we may frame ſuch a thing in God's Decrees) as it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94662:10"/>from that made with <hi>Man,</hi> or Goſpel-Covenant, which requires Faith and Repentance (wrought in us by God's firſt Grace) as the Condition, and upon that Condition, and that as performed by us (though through that Grace) does grant us Remiſſion and Eternal Life. And this firſt Grace God gives to this end, that his <hi>Elect</hi> may in their time enter this Covenant, and ſo have the benefits of it.</p>
               <p>I ſignified this to Mr. <hi>W.</hi> in my Sheet, but he (in his) is ſo full of himſelf, as he will take his Friends by the halves. <hi>I never wrote</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that Faith and Repentance are not Covenant-Bleſſings:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> I perceive thought, and ſo do I, that this is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to what he ſhould write. No Man can have any <hi>Benefit</hi> of the Covenant that is not in Covenant. That which is given of God to his Elect, as pre-requiſite to enter Covenant, is given them before they are in Covenant, and therefore is not any of the Benefits of it. This is what I meant, and I for my part therefore do ſay, that Faith and Repentance are the <hi>Conditions</hi> and not the <hi>Benefits</hi> of the Goſpel-Covenant. For if they be granted Bleſſings thereof, then is there no Condition to its Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and ſo the Covenant is not Conditional according to the ſenſe of thoſe that oppoſe us. The Benefits of the Covenant are God's part to perform, and if Faith and Repentance were part of thoſe Benefits, it were well indeed for us, for then muſt all within the Church be ſaved: The Miniſter does on God's part <hi>declare</hi> the Covenant in his Preaching the Word, and <hi>Seals</hi> it in delivery of the Sacraments, and that to every one: If every one therefore hath not this Faith and Repentance given him, either this Faith and Repentance is not indeed one of the <hi>Benefits,</hi> or God is not Faithful in <hi>Covenant</hi> (this Univerſal Goſpel-Covenant) which cannot be argued, but with a reverential Averſation.</p>
               <p>He hath one thing a little higher to the ſame effect. <hi>Sir, you omit one part of the Objection, that I ſhould ſay the Conditions are Legal. I never called them ſo: I give five Inſtances of the difference between the Condition of the Covenant of Works, and Grace.</hi> Here is our Cauſe yielding ſtill, but I muſt beg his Pardon, for he ſays in this he knows not what. The Inſtances he mentions are nothing to the purpoſe: And as he ſaid before, he never wrote that Faith and Repentance are not Benefits of the Covenant, when he ſhould have wrote ſo: So he ſays here, he never called them Legal Conditions, when he needed not ſcruple it. Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> put in the word <hi>Legal</hi> in oppoſition only to <hi>Teſtamentary;</hi> and when he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94662:11"/>grants a Teſtamentary Condition, he does, I count, under a more ſoft word, ingenuouſly grant us our Point. It is in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s <hi>Peaceable Enquiry,</hi> which Mr. <hi>W.</hi> it ſeems knows not. To Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> then I ſay, If I have an Eſtate given me by Will or Teſtament upon a certain Condition, I muſt perform that Condition, or elſe I cannot have that Eſtate though it be Gift: But the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being performed, it gives me Right to that Eſtate by that Teſtament, and the Law will make it good. It is ſo as to a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> and as to the <hi>Covenant.</hi> The <hi>Performance</hi> gives us Right by (not its own Merit, but vertue of) that <hi>Promiſe,</hi> that <hi>Covenant.</hi> This <hi>I affirm</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>W.</hi> himſelf) <hi>the Promiſe conveighs the Title as ſoon as the Terms of the Grant are anſwered,</hi> Goſpel Truth, p. 61. That thing which being performed gives Right to the Benefit, is a true legal Condition in Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s ſenſe. There is nothing elſe to be underſtood by it. <hi>Legal</hi> is not oppoſed here to <hi>Evangelical</hi> but to <hi>Not rightful.</hi> As I ſaid therefore but now, that Faith and Repentance are not the <hi>Benefits,</hi> but the <hi>Conditions</hi> of the Goſpel-Covenant: So ſay I they are <hi>Antecedent legal</hi> (Evangelically legal, legal in the ſenſe of Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s ſeeming denial thereof) <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of thoſe <hi>Benefits.</hi> And this I did not omit, as Mr. <hi>W.</hi> thinks, but did <hi>de induſtria</hi> own it in my Sheet in theſe words. <hi>If we do not make Faith ſuch a Condition as Antecedes the Benefits, and that being performed gives right to them, that we may not mince the matter</hi> (whereby I meant the aforeſaid diſtinction) <hi>it is but trifling to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the Covenant hath any Conditions.</hi> If we confeſs our Sins, God is Juſt and Faithful to forgive them. They have right to the Tree of Life that keep his Commandments.</p>
               <p>To return then now to the new Heart, promiſed in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael, when the days come</hi> that they may enter this Covenant ſo as to break it no more, I have one thing to offer here to publick conſideration. Our Divines interpret theſe Texts to belong to the Elect, to them only, all the Elect, (with whom this Covenant is made from Eternity in Chriſt, ſay ſome, ſuppoſing <hi>This,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Redemption</hi> to be one.) Now it is to me a queſtion whether they be not quite out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is manifeſt in all the places in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and that to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that this Promiſe and Covenant to be made, is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar ſtill to the Jews, and that confined to a certain time (<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the days come, ſaith the Lord</hi>) which is expreſſed over and over after their ſcattering and recollection. Let us look the Scripture. The firſt Text that we have, wherein this Abſolute
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94662:11"/>Promiſe is to be found, is in <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>And the Lord thy God will circumciſe thine heart, and the heart of thy Seed.</hi> Well, but when will the Lord do this? They were almoſt all uncircumciſed in Heart at preſent, and continued ſo during their Judges, their Kings, and Prophets. Look therefore to the Verſes before, and <hi>Moſes</hi> is Prophecying of their State hereafter, that they would Sin and God would ſcatter them, and then gather them after from all Nations, and bring them to the Land <hi>which their Fathers poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed</hi> (ſpeaking this before they came into Poſſeſſion) and in that State it is he promiſes this Circumciſion of their Heart, ſo as they ſhall <hi>love him</hi> with the <hi>whole</hi> of it, and <hi>live,</hi> and fall no more from him.</p>
               <p>Let us come from <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Prophets, ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19, 20. <hi>I will give them one heart, and put a new Spirit in them, and I will take away the ſtony heart that they may walk in my Ordinances, and they ſhall be my People, and I will be their God.</hi> Here is the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> but to whom? Why <hi>all the whole Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>wholly are they,</hi> v. 15. Even the ſcattered afar off among the Countries, <hi>v.</hi> 16. And when is it to be fulfilled? <hi>I will gather you from the People, and aſſemble you out of the Countries where you have been ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and I will give you the Land of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>v.</hi> 17. Likewiſe in Chap. 36. v. 22. to 28. <hi>Say to the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, O <hi>Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>I will take you from among the Heathen, and gather you from all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and will bring you to your own Land. Then will I ſprinkle clean water on you, and a new Spirit, and take away the heart of stone, and cauſe you to walk in my Statutes, and ye ſhall be my People, and I will be your God.</hi> From <hi>Ezekiel</hi> let us go to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Jer. 32.37. <hi>I will gather them,</hi> (the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah, v.</hi> 30.) <hi>out of all Countries wither I have driven them in my Anger, and bring them again to this place; I will give them one heart and one way, that they may fear me for ever. And I will make an everlaſting Covenant with them, and they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> In <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>And it ſhall be at that day thou ſhalt call me</hi> Iſhi, v. 16. <hi>And in that day I will make a Covenant,</hi> v. 18. <hi>And I will betroth thee for ever,</hi> v. 19. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day I will hear,</hi> v. 21. Well! and when is that day? Look <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.14, 15. <hi>Behold, the dayes come, ſaith the Lord, that it ſhall no more be ſaid, the Lord liveth that brought up the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>out of</hi> Egypt: <hi>But the Lord liveth that brought up the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>from the Land of the North, and from all Lands whether he had driven them: And I will bring them again into their Land that I gave their Fathers.</hi> Thus much is apparent, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94662:12"/>this new Heart and new Covenant is promiſed, it is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Jews upon a Reſtauration. Let us look laſtly then into the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> which cites another Text out of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Heb. 8 8. <hi>Finding fault with them</hi> (in regard to the firſt Covenant) <hi>he ſaith, Behold the days come, ſaith the Lord, when I will make a new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Houſe of</hi> Judah: <hi>Not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that I made with their Fathers in the day that I lead them out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>becauſe they continued not in it, and I regarded them not.</hi> And ſo goes on to what I have cited in the beginning, and more follows to the end.</p>
               <p>Here is a Covenant we ſee made with the Jews, which they brake, and God caſts them off; and here is another which he promiſes to be made with them, that they ſhall keep, and he will caſt them off no more; and this time it ſhall be made with them, is when he ſhall gather them from all parts of the World where they are ſcattered, and bring them to their Land again, as it is in all the places here mentioned. <hi>At that time, In that day,</hi> he will give them this new Heart to enter this <hi>new</hi> Covenant (this <hi>ſecond</hi> Covenant, and <hi>with them,</hi> not the ſecond with <hi>Mankind,</hi> which was with us in <hi>Adam</hi> Fallen) <hi>after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And when was that day? Is it paſt? Was it not immediately after the Captivity out of <hi>Babylon?</hi> I judge not, for the Jews that returned then, were thoſe of <hi>Judah</hi> only, not the ſcattered of the whole Houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and theſe alſo in ſome time grew as bad as their Forefathers, <hi>filling up their meaſure,</hi> as Chriſt ſpeaks, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they came to Crucifie the Lord of Life himſelf; and there is no Seaſon yet, wherein ſuch a Heart hath been given them, as in theſe Texts is promiſed, that they ſhould ſo Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as to break it no more. This is certain, that ſince their Sin in Crucifying Chriſt, they have been driven from <hi>Jewry</hi> and diſperſed the World over; and the Promiſe then of gathering them out of all Nations, and giving them this new Heart, thus to Covenant a new (or a ſecond time) with the Lord, is in all likelihood not yet, nor to be accompliſhed, <hi>until the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled,</hi> as Chriſt tells, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.24. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> Comments it, <hi>Until the fulneſs of the Gentiles be come,</hi> Rom. 11.25.</p>
               <p>That there is a time of <hi>Calling the Jews,</hi> is not only an ancient Opinion of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and many of thoſe Fathers that were <hi>Millenaries,</hi> but of our <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divines; and it was much upon the Hearts of thoſe called <hi>Puritans</hi> in their time, it being built on thoſe two Texts now mentioned: And indeed there are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94662:12"/>twenty and twenty places in the Prophets, that ſpeak of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious State of the Jews to come, that none can ſay have yet their Accompliſhment. And if this Opinion of a time to come of <hi>Calling the Jews</hi> be good, then may we well believe that <hi>that</hi> will be the time when theſe Texts, and Promiſe ſtood upon, will be fulfilled. When the Converſion of the Gentiles is brought in to the full of what God has determined (to whom <hi>a thouſand years is but as one day</hi>) then ſhall be the gathering of the ſcattered. And as it is into the <hi>Jews Olive</hi> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are ingrafted, the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall return to that <hi>Olive</hi> themſelves, and both become the Church of Chriſt: So that <hi>All</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be ſaved,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, citing for it that of <hi>Iſaiah, There ſhall come out of</hi> Sion <hi>a Deliverer, and ſhall turn away Ungodlineſs from</hi> Jacob: <hi>For this is my Covenant unto them, when I ſhall take away their ſins,</hi> Rom. 11.26. Note it, the Covenant, called the <hi>new Covenant</hi> in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> is to be made with <hi>Jacob,</hi> that is, his Poſterity, at this time when this Prophecy is accompliſhed, and that is plainly at the <hi>calling of the Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then from what is ſaid I argue, and by virtue of all theſe Scriptures forecited, I do deny that the firſt Grace, Faith and Repentance, or the new Heart, is a Promiſe of the Covenant of Grace made with Mankind, or with the Elect in Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a Promiſe only to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to come, and that at ſuch a time, when hereafter God ſhall gather them into his Church from among the Nations.</p>
               <p>It may be objected, That the very mentioning the Prophecy of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> by the Author to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> does prove it to be applied to his times (it does prove it indeed not to be in any time before, and ſo not at their return from <hi>Babylon</hi>) and that the mentioning that Covenant, does prove it to be meant of the Goſpel-Covenant: But I deny it. The mentioning of a Promiſe made only to the <hi>Jews,</hi> is no proof of it to be made to <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Elect;</hi> and the mention of a Covenant to be made with them <hi>after thoſe days,</hi> is no proof that it is meant of a Covenant made with us at the <hi>preſent day.</hi> He does not ſay as Chriſt did, when he opened the Book at a place prophecying of him, <hi>This day is this Scripture fulfilled in your Ears,</hi> for the day is not yet come, the day of God's making this ſecond Covenant with the Jews (for I muſt inculcate that it is a <hi>ſecond</hi> as to them) only the Author cites the Prophecy in reſpect to his matter in hand, which is, that the Jewiſh Diſpenſation, their <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> was already
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94662:13"/>ceaſed, the Promiſe of a <hi>new</hi> to come, ſhewing its intended Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment. Which arguing is good, and becoming Sacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, though the time be to come. For there's nothing here argued but at preſent is true, notwithſtanding the <hi>peculiarity</hi> of this Prophecy is yet to be made good. The Covenant of Grace in the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it, is one and the ſame ſince <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall to this day, and to this time yet to be accompliſhed: But the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe <hi>Adminiſtrations</hi> of it were to be at ſeveral Seaſons. It was in the <hi>Promiſe</hi> only till Chriſt, and then he <hi>ratified</hi> it by his Blood, and <hi>promulgated</hi> it by his Apoſtles, which all ſtands good very conſiſtently with <hi>another Adminiſtration</hi> (as to them) upon the <hi>Jews Vocation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know now there are twenty Queſtions might be raiſed here by way of Objection, or for the ſake of Elucidation, which I was a little thinking upon, but I will leave them every one to others Meditations. If what I have ſtarted be good, there is an end of all Difficulty in regard to the <hi>Conditionality</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel-Covenant,</hi> and what I or others have anſwered to thoſe Texts may be ſpared: For there is nothing conſiderable but from theſe Texts that is againſt us. I conclude, If it be good, there is ſome body or other, at ſome time or other, will make it good: If it be not good, I will be at my liberty to ſtand where I do, and disbelieve it again as well as any other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>PART III</head>
               <p>IN the Point of Juſtification Mr. <hi>W.</hi> made this grant, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming upon it in this Paper, he tells me, <hi>I have truly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented his words,</hi> to wit, that <hi>Beſides the Effects being made ours, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to Believers,</hi> though I told him, (<hi>Mid. way of Juſt.</hi> p. 56.) that this (as far as I can ſee) is to bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and yield our Cauſe to his Adverſaries. It is in vain really (if it be not ſinful daubing to be bewailed in the conſequence of it) for Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to argue againſt Chriſt's <hi>Suretiſhip,</hi> and <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Perſons</hi> in the ill ſenſe, which he intends only to confute, when that ill ſenſe, and all that the <hi>Antinomian</hi> ſays beſides de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on this Suppoſition, that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is made ours more, or otherwiſe, than in the Effects. For my part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I do plainly here, as plainly before, ſay, that if our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines will have any other Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94662:13"/>than <hi>quoad fructus &amp; effectus,</hi> they muſt for me have none at all. For when the Phraſe, of the <hi>Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs,</hi> is not once found in Scripture, it muſt be <hi>gratis</hi> allowed them; and if they will not accept this, I can allow no more.</p>
               <p>To open my ſelf, The common Opinion of Proteſtants is, that we are Juſtified by the Imputation of Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and that this Righteouſneſs is imputed ſo, as God does reckon Chriſt's Righteouſneſs for ours, that it may anſwer the Law of Works, according to which they conceive we are to be Juſtified. As the Scripture ſays Faith is imputed for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo do they think Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is: For they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Faith <hi>Objectivé in ſenſu correlativo,</hi> for Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs received by Faith: When the Scripture ſays no where that his Righteouſneſs is imputed (as I noted but now,) and much leſs that it is <hi>imputed for Righteouſneſs,</hi> there being no good Senſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of which is like to hold.</p>
               <p>Of theſe Divines, ſome and the moſt do underſtand by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, the Righteouſneſs of his Life and Death, his Active and Paſſive Obedience both. God does reckon us (ſay they) to have ſuffered the Penalty of the Law in his Death, and ſo we are free from Condemnation: And being <hi>Recti in curia,</hi> there is required father a Righteouſneſs of perfect Obedience to this Law for a Right to Heaven, and ſo his Active Obedience is imputed alſo.</p>
               <p>Others being convinced of a manifeſt Inconſiſtency here (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if the <hi>Active Obedience</hi> of Chriſt be imputed to us, which is to reckon us, that we have neither omitted any Duty, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any Sin, there needs no Imputation of his <hi>Sufferings,</hi>) they maintain that Chriſt's Active Obedience was <hi>Juſtitia Perſonae,</hi> a Righteouſneſs neceſſary to himſelf as a Man to fulfil: But his Paſſive (ſeeing he was Sinleſs) was, and muſt be for us only, and in our ſtead, and that is the <hi>Juſtitia meriti</hi> which is imputed to Sinners for their Juſtification. It is the choiceſt of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines beyond Sea, next <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> that go this way.</p>
               <p>But there have been ſome more pondering Thoughts on this Doctrine of <hi>Imputation,</hi> by ſuch as apprehend, that as the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt being an Accident inhering in him as its proper Subject, and incapable to be in us alſo, ſo neither can it be <hi>in ſe imputed</hi> to us, or reckoned ſo as ours, whether it be the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of his Life or Death. To be accounted of God to be as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94662:14"/>Righteous as Chriſt himſelf, is too hard of Digeſtion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will allow an Imputation, but underſtand it ſenſibly, that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is indeed <hi>imputed</hi> to Believers, but not <hi>in ſe</hi> as ours in it ſelf, but ſo as to be ours only in the Fruits and Effects. Thus that maſterfully learned Man <hi>Forbs</hi> in his <hi>Modeſtae queſtiones,</hi> and ſome others: Which giving Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> the Notion, he hath ſo cultivated it, delivering his Judgment that way, and that in ſo many Books, and ſo largely, as it is hard for any to gainſay, or to ſay that he does fully comprehend him.</p>
               <p>He hath prudently uſed <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> as to the making up Chriſt's Satisfaction of both Obediences Active and Paſſive, according to that Mediatorial Covenant (as we ſpeak of it) between his Father and him. For this was the Father's Pleaſure or Mediato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Command <hi>(This Commandment I received of my Father)</hi> that he ſhould repair the Honour of his broken Law, and anſwer the ends of it, by a perfect obeying of it, and ſuffering for Man's Sin againſt it, and thereby Merit to all Mankind (it being done in their behalf) a Right to Pardon and Salvation, or to Impunity and Life; which yet is to be given them upon ſuch Terms as ſhould pleaſe him and the Redeemer; for ſo long as it was not the Perſons themſelves that obeyed and ſuffered, but another in their ſtead, (and that by way of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> not ſtrict <hi>Payment,</hi>) the Benefit of that Obedience and Suffering might be diſpoſed at their Will. Now this Right to Impunity and Life obtained, is given or granted in an Act of Grace, declared in the Goſpel, which runs thus, that whoſoever he be that Believes, Repents, and lives ſincerely according to it, ſhall be pardoned and ſaved.</p>
               <p>Even as in an Act of Pardon by Parliament, a Man hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Treaſon or the like, the Treaſon is ſtill by the Law Death, but upon ſuch an Act paſſing, thoſe Perſons that are guilty are pardoned, if qualified according to the Act: In like manner that Man who performs this Goſpel-Condition, hath this Right by vertue of this Act, Law (or Covenant) of Grace, Grant, Deed of Gift, Will of Chriſt, Teſtament, or Goſpel. The Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt is the Meritorious Cauſe of it, and this Act of Grace, the Inſtrument of Donation, or Law-title.</p>
               <p>Here then we ſee is a Righteouſneſs Evangelical that we have and muſt have, and here is a Right to Impunity and Life (which you may if you will call a Righteouſneſs too) that we have alſo: But the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt we have here only in <hi>the Effect.</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94662:14"/>As in the common inſtance, I have a Friend made Slave in <hi>Algiers,</hi> I give a 100 <hi>l.</hi> for his Ranſom, he never has, nor ſees the 100 <hi>l.</hi> but the Money is his in the Liberty he poſſeſſeth.</p>
               <p>Note, When the former ſort of Divines mentioned ſay, that by the Imputation of Chriſt's Death to us, we become <hi>recti in Curia,</hi> and there muſt be then a Righteouſneſs of his Life imputed farther, to entitle us to Heaven, they underſtand ſtill that it is by the <hi>Law of Works</hi> that we are to be tried and judged: But let all underſtand aright (as before) that it is by the <hi>Law of Grace,</hi> and ſuppoſing then we were thereby <hi>recti in curia,</hi> that Righteouſneſs required farther unto this Title, muſt be the Righteouſneſs of that Law we are judged by, to wit, our Evangelical Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs only, which is accepted unto Life (or made the <hi>Condition</hi>) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>that</hi> of the Law, upon the account of this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>We muſt diſtinguiſh here, to avoid Prejudice, (and leaſt the tender be offended.) There is the <hi>Duty,</hi> and the <hi>Condition</hi> of this <hi>Law,</hi> the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> the Law of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> by which we are to be judged. God hath conſtituted the Duty, the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Reward, the Penalty of it. There are few of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and much leſs of our People, are ſenſible of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage this Doctrine brings us, and the Soundneſs of it. No Man we muſt know does perform the <hi>Duty,</hi> but every Man muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the <hi>Condition,</hi> or he cannot be ſaved. This Condition (as obtained for the World) is the grand Benefit of Chriſt's Purchaſe, or main Fruit of his Death, and is accepted when performed, only through him. It is not for my Works or Merits, <hi>ſayeſt thou,</hi> that <hi>my Perſon is accepted,</hi> but for Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and in this alone is my Comfort. And <hi>I ſay,</hi> it is not for the Works ſake, or Merit of any thing, or all we do, but for Chriſt's ſake, that <hi>the Condition is accepted;</hi> and it is in this is <hi>my</hi> Comfort: In this it is that we have, or can have, any grounded Suſtentation. To ſay thou art Juſtified by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, when yet thou muſt acknowledge his Righteouſneſs is none of thine, unleſs thou haſt performed the Condition, What empty Comfort is that? But to ſay that through Chriſt's Merits and Righteouſneſs, this it ſelf that I do, is the Condition; here is Comfort indeed. That what we are enabled by his Grace (I ſay) to do, how little ſoever, if ſincerely done (if it be but the Grain of <hi>Muſtard-ſeed</hi> in a <hi>hungring and thirſting after Righteouſneſs,</hi>) ſhall be accepted unto Life (that is, be <hi>that Condition</hi>) upon account of what Chriſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94662:15"/>hath done for us, this I ſay is ſolid Conſolation. Thou ſaiſt, when I look on my Works my Heart ſinks, I am not ſure I am Sincere, but in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt I am ſafe. I ſay this is certain, If thou art not Sincere, thou art not Safe: And when I doubt whether I am or not, I can have no Support but in this, that I hope I am, I truſt I am; and that it is upon the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Merit of Chriſt, that Faith, that Hope does depend. For, that there is any Condition at all, that the Condition is ſuch, that what I do ſhall be accepted as the Condition per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, it muſt all be put upon the account of Chriſt's Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, or Merit, in our behalf; and his Merit is ſufficient, however imperfect be our Duty, for its Acceptance with God. When then upon a Senſe of my Deficiency, inſtead of ſinking, I grow bolder in my reliance on Chriſt's Merits, and God's Mercy, I do not preſume on my ſelf, but I magnifie his Grace, and the higher I raiſe my Faith thereupon (provided I live not willingly in any Conſcience-waſting Sin) the more Glory (am I humbly perſwaded) do I give my gracious Saviour, and good God. Thou Man, haſt the Comfort to apply <hi>to thy ſelf</hi> Chriſt's Merits, if thou haſt performed the Condition: But I have the Comfort to apply Chriſt's Merits <hi>to the Condition,</hi> which makes his <hi>Yoke eaſie</hi> and <hi>burden light,</hi> as to the Performance; and my very Deſires and weakeſt Endeavours to find Acceptance.</p>
               <p>When I read ſuch Prayers of <hi>David,</hi> that God would not <hi>enter into Judgment</hi> with him, that he would not be <hi>extream to mark</hi> what he had done <hi>amiſs,</hi> for then he <hi>could not abide</hi> it, and that yet he will have God to <hi>ſearch him,</hi> and <hi>try his Reins and Heart,</hi> and the like, I cannot but be convinced, that in the Acceptance of ſuch an imperfect Righteouſneſs as he accounted his was, through God's meer gracious Condeſcention, Mercy and Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him, he placed his<note n="*" place="margin">That there is a Righteouſneſs ſet forth in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as another Righteouſneſs than that of the <hi>Law,</hi> by which we are to be juſtified, is ſignally affirmed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21, 23. <hi>Now is the Righteouſneſs of God revealed.</hi> The doing what the Law requires, and nothing leſs, is Righteouſneſs, the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Man</hi> I will call it. If any one did that, it would and muſt juſtifie him. <hi>The Doers of the Law before God are juſtified,</hi> Rom. 2.13. The Apoſtle ſtill ſo accounts (which we muſt know) and tells us thereupon, that no Man, <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> does it, but that all fall ſhort thereof, in his three firſt Chapters to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and conſequently by their <hi>Works</hi> cannot be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified. Upon this ground is it, that he oppoſes <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> ſo often as he does in the buſineſs of Juſtification. <hi>By Grace are ye ſaved, not of Works,</hi> Eph. 2.8, 9. <hi>Who hath ſaved us, not according to our Works, but his Grace,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.9. <hi>If by Grace then not of Works,</hi> Rom. 11.6. <hi>Not by Works of Righteouſneſs which we have done, but according to his Mercy he ſaved us,</hi> and yet by <hi>Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (it follows) <hi>and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Tit. 3.5. How is that? Are we ſaved by (at leaſt not without) Works wrought in us by the Spirit or Grace which regenerates us, and yet, <hi>Not of Works?</hi> Again, <hi>Not of Works, leaſt any Man ſhould boaſt</hi> (Eph. 2.9, 10.) yet it follows, <hi>we are created in Chriſt Jeſus to good Works.</hi> To anſwer this, St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and from him the Schools, diſtinguiſh of <hi>Opera Naturae,</hi> and <hi>Opera Gratiae.</hi> We are not ſaved by Works, or according to Works done <hi>in our own ſtrength,</hi> but by Works done <hi>by Grace.</hi> But is this the Apoſtles meaning? No, I have ſhewn in my Book of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> that one thing of three wherein <hi>Auſtine</hi> was out, and hath miſlead the Schools, is this Notion of <hi>Grace.</hi> By grace he underſtands ſtill this inherent Grace, or Operation of God's Spirit in us, when <hi>Paul</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it of that without us, his Favour, or Condeſcention to us. Not of <hi>Works</hi> but of <hi>Grace,</hi> is all one, as not of <hi>Deſert</hi> but of <hi>Favour</hi> only. Grace is <hi>Mercy without, or contrary to Merit.</hi> Now when the Papiſt receives the Solution mentioned, the Proteſtant generally will have all <hi>Works,</hi> though of the <hi>Regneerate,</hi> to be but <hi>Rags,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt's Righteouſneſs</hi> alone to ſave us. But they are both out, for <hi>Paul</hi>'s meaning is plainer than they think. <hi>Not by Works of Righteouſneſs we have done.</hi> The Righteouſneſs which the Jew hath <hi>done,</hi> is living accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> The Righteouſneſs which the Gentile hath <hi>done,</hi> is his living ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of <hi>Nature.</hi> There is neither one or the other that fulfil that Righteouſneſs as anſwers God's Law, ſo as it ſhould be able to ſave him, and therefore it is of <hi>Grace</hi> or <hi>Mercy,</hi> that any are ſaved. By this Key muſt that hard Text alſo be opened, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. <hi>So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth Mercy.</hi> What? Is there any that find Mercy, or are ſaved, but they that <hi>will</hi> and <hi>run?</hi> I anſwer No, but there is none of them that <hi>will</hi> and <hi>run,</hi> do will and run ſo as would ſave them, if God did not pardon their Failings, and accept their Endeavours through the Merits of Chriſt. The meaning is, that ſeeing no Man hath thoſe Works the Law requires to Salvation, it is of <hi>Grace</hi> or of <hi>Mercy,</hi> that we are accepted to Life on <hi>Another Condition.</hi>
                     <p>Well now, it being of <hi>Grace</hi> that we are Saved or Juſtified in oppoſition to <hi>Work's,</hi> and it being neceſſary that thoſe Works be underſtood of ſuch as the Law requires to Juſtifie us, that is, Perfect Works, Meritorious Works, which if we had, we might <hi>boaſt,</hi> and expect the Reward <hi>as of Debt;</hi> and the reaſon why we are not juſtified by Works, being becauſe we have them not, it follows, that there is <hi>another Righteouſneſs</hi> which is to be had, ſhort of that the Law requires to Juſtification, not Perfect, not Meritorious, not ſuch as would make the Reward due of Juſtice, but ſuch as needs Grace for the Acceptance, (<hi>Therefore it is of Faith that it might be of Grace,</hi>) and that I ſay which we muſt have; for God cannot account a Man Righteous (which is to juſtifie him) that is not Righteous, his Judgment being accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Truth. And what Righteouſneſs then is that a Man muſt have, and be found in, but that we call our Evangelical Righteouſneſs, the Righteouſneſs of Faith? <hi>The Juſt ſhall live by Faith.</hi> Note it, he is <hi>Juſt, Righteous,</hi> that <hi>lives,</hi> or is Juſtified: But how Righteous? Not according to the <hi>Law,</hi> but the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> Hence is the Goſpel called the <hi>Miniſtration of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs:</hi> Hence do we read of a <hi>Righteouſneſs brought in</hi> by the Meſſiah ſlain in <hi>Daniel:</hi> Hence that we are <hi>choſen in Chriſt to be Holy,</hi> That he hath redeemed us from Iniquity, That the end (or one end) of his Death or Redemption is to <hi>make us Righteous,</hi> as our Divines ſtill ſay, but I never found any ſatisfactory account of it by them. The matter in ſhort is (you may ſee it fuller in my mentioned Book, p. 43.) that by Chriſt's Death a Law of <hi>Grace</hi> is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, upon which our Faith and Repentance is accepted to Life, or <hi>imputed for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or we made Righteous ſo, when by the Law of <hi>Works</hi> there is none, <hi>no not one</hi> Righteous, or ever could be, in the World. Hence is this Righteouſneſs called <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> as being ordained and accepted by him, inſtead of (that I even now called) the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Man:</hi> And <hi>which is of God by Faith,</hi> inſtead of ſuch <hi>Works</hi> which the Law required to Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Hence laſtly are we ſaid to be <hi>Juſtified by Faith,</hi> the moſt ſingle and plain reaſon whereof is, becauſe that <hi>Faith</hi> to a true Believer, is <hi>imputed for Righteouſneſs,</hi> (Rom. 4.22, 23, 24.) And Faith is ſaid to be imputed to him <hi>for Righteouſneſs,</hi> becauſe God does account ſuch a one Righteous, and deals with him as ſuch, in freeing him from Puniſhment, and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to Salvation, through the Death and Obedience of our Redeemer.</p>
                  </note> Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in which ſenſe alſo he calls him <hi>the God of his Righteouſneſs:</hi> When as for any acceptance of him through the Righteouſneſs of the Meſſiah to come, a Righteouſneſs without him made his by Faith, which could abide God's diſtrict Juſtice, I find not the Footſtep of one ſuch Thought. To rely therefore (I will ſay) on Chriſt's Righteouſneſs as ours, without regard
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94662:15"/>to any thing <hi>within,</hi> or without regard to the <hi>Condition,</hi> is <hi>ſelf-deceiving:</hi> But to rely on God's Mercy, and on Chriſt's Merits, for acceptance of what we do, and Pardon for the Failings, is <hi>Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Religion;</hi> and of <hi>Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt's Blood,</hi> a good Expoſition.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94662:16"/>
               <p>I have now ſomething more to be farther pondered on this Point. The chief is, That what I have ſaid before about the <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> that it is to be held in regard to the <hi>Impetration,</hi> not <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of our Redemption, I would offer over again likewiſe, in regard to the <hi>Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs.</hi> I have ſaid, and ſay it over, that this Phraſe is not found in Scripture, but I will acknowledge the thing in the true ſenſe of it, which is this. Chriſt Jeſus did really obey the Law, and ſuffer its Penalty <hi>for us,</hi> which is, in <hi>our place</hi> or <hi>ſtead.</hi> To do a thing now in my ſtead, is for another to do it, ſo as to ſave me the doing it. Chriſt's Suffering and Obeying, was to ſave us that Suffering and Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. No, ſays Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſomewhere, <hi>Christ ſuffered indeed in our ſtead, that we might not ſuffer, but not obeyed that we might not obey.</hi> But if Chriſt obeyed not that we might not obey, he obeyed not <hi>in our ſtead.</hi> How is it then? Why Chriſt obeyed the Law, as the perfect Obedience thereof required was the Condition of Life, and by his obeying it thus, he hath freed us from being under that Condition, that is, from ſo obeying it (as by his Suffering we are freed from enduring the Curſe:) Not by a Ceſſation of the Duty, or Sanction (Premiant or Penal) of the Law of <hi>Works;</hi> but by the Acceſſion of the Law of <hi>Grace,</hi> becauſe the Sanction of <hi>that</hi> Law is remedied by <hi>this,</hi> both being in Chriſt's hands, neither abrogating the other. To be freed from the Obligation of perfect Obedience, as the Condition of Life does import, or is all one as, or with, to be freed from the Commination of Death upon the leaſt failing thereof; ſo that the Promiſory part of that Law, and Comminatory part, are alike concerned, and muſt be underſtood both alike to be of force, or ceaſe, as before ſhewn. By Chriſt's Sufferings we are not freed from all Sufferings, or Puniſhment for Sin, but from ſuffering the <hi>Curſe</hi> in that Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94662:16"/>So by his Obedience we are not freed from endeavouring and doing what we can to become perfect, but we are freed from the Obligation of the Performance, as neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
               <p>This comes in by the way, but for the <hi>Imputation</hi> now of <hi>Chriſt's Righteouſneſs,</hi> Chriſt ſuffered and obeyed <hi>for us</hi> I ſay, which muſt be underſtood aright. Not that God looks on us, as if we our ſelves had obeyed or ſuffered either in his Perſon, or he to have done it <hi>ſtrictly</hi> in ours; but that he obeyed and ſuffered <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> to free us from ſo Obeying and Suffering as he himſelf did, which is the making his Death and Obedience ours only as to this Benefit. Thus much being right, and the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt conſiſting in this Obedience, and ſuffering of this in our room, now what at laſt is the <hi>Imputation</hi> of it? Why certainly the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, is and muſt be nothing elſe, but God's accounting the matter to be thus as it is. Here is the Point, That what Chriſt hath done, is lookt upon, is accepted as done in our behalf, or the granting it to be ſo; that upon this Obeying and Suffering of his in our place, as the <hi>Meritorious Cauſe,</hi> we ſhall be freed from the ſame Obedience and Suffering our ſelves, as the <hi>Effect</hi> of it. This is the only Fundamental Truth in the Phraſe, and this Imputation then of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs (which Man hath ſo phraſed) going into this Grant on God's part, or obtaining the Grant on Chriſt's part, which precedes the Application, it cannot go into the Application it ſelf (that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows after upon the Performance of the Goſpel-terms) ſo as to make Chriſt's Righteouſneſs ours, any otherwiſe than in this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit only.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, the fancying ſuch Acts in God, as the imputing Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to every ſingle Perſon upon his Believing, any otherwiſe than by that one Act of Grace now promulgated in the Goſpel, is not becoming the Divine Being. There is, there can be no new Acts in God: He is <hi>Actus purus,</hi> his Will one. I muſt not grow too Subtle here, only I muſt ſay there is his <hi>Will,</hi> and the <hi>Effects</hi> of his Will, and in thoſe Effects there is an Order. In that Order the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt precedes the Impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Benefits we have by him, as the Meritorious Cauſe of them; and the Impetration precedes the Application, and the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs going to the Impetration, the Application cannot but be of the Effects thereof: Not of this <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> (I ſay) <hi>it ſelf (in ſe,)</hi> but of the <hi>Benefits themſelves</hi> we have by it.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94662:17"/>
               <p>To be more ſhort, That Commutation of Perſons, and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, (which come both in earneſt to this one ſame thing, <hi>Mans Benefit for Chriſt's Satisfaction</hi>) how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Thoughts thereof have amuſed ſo many good Men, when you have throughly conſidered them, and made as much of them as ever you can, it muſt all of it, every drop of it you can make, go into that Act of Grace (<hi>Salvation upon Goſpel-Conditions</hi>) which is <hi>already</hi> procured and paſſed. Unto the <hi>Impetration</hi> then of our Redemption, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs was indeed imputed <hi>in it ſelf:</hi> In the <hi>Application</hi> it can be imputed only in the <hi>Effects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know there are ſome Texts, very high Texts, about this matter in Scripture, ſuch as theſe, <hi>He hath made him Sin for us, that we may be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him. By the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of one many ſhall be made Righteous. Chriſt is the end of the Law to the Believer.</hi> What is the meaning of ſuch Texts? The meaning really I take to be but the ſame I have now opened. They all come to this, That Chriſt by his Satisfaction and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, hath procured us ſuch a Freedom from the Law, that <hi>Faith without Works</hi> (that is, Legal Works) may be <hi>imputed to us for Righteouſneſs,</hi> which is all one as that we may become Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous upon performing only the Terms of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law.</hi> How? I anſwer, If I ſay, by putting an end to it, I ſpeak what is plaineſt. This is to give <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> its own proper Interpretation. But how hath Chriſt done that? He hath done it by ſatisfying and obeying it (I have ſaid) in our ſtead. He hath by the Merit of his Obedience procured our Deliverance from the Obligation to perfect Obedience as the Condition of Life. This is ſuch an end of the Law as will hold, and can never be contradicted. I will confirm it with the words following, <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law, for Righteouſneſs to him that believeth.</hi> There are two Queſtions here will go to the heart of this Text: <hi>What</hi> is the end of the Law, and <hi>Why</hi> there is an end of it? For the <hi>What</hi> we ſee, The end of the Law is this Fredom (as I ſay) from the Condition mentioned. For the <hi>Why,</hi> the Text ſays it is <hi>for Righteouſneſs to him that believeth.</hi> Now what is the meaning of theſe words? It is that by believing we make Chriſt's Righteouſneſs ours, and thereby are Juſtified? No, it is that by believing (true believing, which is alſo obeying the Goſpel) we may be (<hi>made,</hi> as one of the Texts has it) <hi>Righteous,</hi> and being ſo, be accounted ſo of God, and dealt with as ſo, not Legally, but Evangelically ſo, and accepted in that <hi>Righteouſneſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94662:17"/>of God</hi> (See my Book of <hi>Juſtif.</hi> p. 57, 58.) oppoſed to the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Works,</hi> unto Eternal Life. This St. <hi>John</hi> teaches, <hi>He that doeth Righteouſneſs is Righteous,</hi> and Chriſt's own mouth hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>And the Righteous to Life Everlaſting.</hi> As for that Text which is like ſtill to be laid in our way, the firſt of thoſe that in the words I have quoted, (to wit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.) I will accumulate thus much, that, <hi>In Chriſt's taking on him our Sins, to become a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for them, and fulfilling the Law, to procure thoſe new terms, in performance whereof we are accepted as Righteous through his Merits,</hi> does the <hi>Commutation</hi> we find there conſiſt; yea, as I have inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated a little before, even that whole <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> with which our Brethren do ſo puzzle themſelves, and vex Mr. <hi>W.</hi> I would not have them offended with me as with him, though I ſpeak out what he does not, that, here in good earneſt is the full of the matter, and (excepting the Darkneſs of Prejudice, which in moſt is as dark as Pit) there is no more in it.</p>
               <p>This being ſo, I muſt not admit any ſuch Interpretation of the place, that is framed according to our common Doctrine, which teaches, that by Faith we receive Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, that this receiving makes it ours; and that God then reckons us, as having performed the Condition of the Law in Chriſt, and ſo juſtifies us by it. All which is quite <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>words</hi> of this <hi>Text,</hi> that ſays, <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law;</hi> and to this <hi>meaning,</hi> in regard to its <hi>Condition,</hi> ſeeing this Doctrine makes the <hi>Law</hi> to have <hi>no end,</hi> but to ſtand to the great day; and that by <hi>this Condition</hi> we are to be Juſtified, ſubverting not only this Text, but the whole Goſpel. This yet is moſt evident in the Verſes following, for the Apoſtle diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Law,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> makes this Righteouſneſs to be the <hi>confeſſing with the Mouth,</hi> and <hi>believing with the Heart,</hi> which are Acts of ours, and not the Obedience of Chriſt without us imputed: So that if you ſhall give <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> any other ſignification than this, the Scope yet and Purpoſe of the place muſt be the ſame. I have ſtaid ſo long on this Text, becauſe I have omitted it, when I paraphraſed the others in my Book of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> where all I ſay here, and more, is made out.</p>
               <p>I know there are Divines, who make Juſtification to lye in Pardon altogether, and ſay we are <hi>made Righteous</hi> in ſuch Texts, only by being pardoned. The being freed (ſay they) from the Guilt of all Sin, both of Omiſſion and Commiſſion, does intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Righteouſneſs, as the expelling Darkneſs does Light, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94662:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>for a Sinner to be juſtified or <hi>made Righteous,</hi> muſt be by a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in regard to the <hi>Sanction</hi> of the Law, when in regard to the <hi>Preceptive part,</hi> no Man is Righteous in <hi>himſelf</hi> or in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe Suretiſhip does reach ſo far and no farther. This do they indeed very cleverly ſay: Nevertheleſs I am convinced, that the Apoſtle by <hi>Juſtification</hi> (when he diſcourſes of it to be by <hi>Faith</hi> and not <hi>Works</hi>) means not <hi>Pardon,</hi> which is an <hi>Effect</hi> thereof (I count) not <hi>the formal reaſon.</hi> I have one Argument for this convinces me in my Book of <hi>Juſtification</hi> (the late ſecond Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 48.) which yet another perhaps may frame for me ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better. I obſerve alſo that the Scripture denominates Men Righteous ſtill from their <hi>walking uprightly,</hi> not from <hi>Pardon,</hi> P. 22. I have more elaborately evinced, that the Righteouſneſs of <hi>God</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Works</hi> is <hi>this,</hi> that I ſtand upon P. 27, 40, 57, 58. And upon the ſame account (I have added farther in a Note here) is the Goſpel called the <hi>Miniſtration of Righteouſneſs.</hi> See what I there offer (P. 43.) if it doth not evince it. By ſuch Notices as theſe (which <hi>aliunde</hi> too, I muſt ſay, I have not had) am I confirmed in my own Opinion.</p>
               <p>Another word ſtill with Mr. <hi>W.</hi> That God does look upon us (or account) that we Suffered and made Satisfaction legally in Chriſt's Perſon, or that Chriſt Suffered and made Satisfaction ſtrictly in our Perſons (which I count to be all one, or hitherto have,) and yet that Chriſt ſuffered in our place or ſtead, Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and I both hold. Now both theſe I take to be conſiſtent, becauſe Chriſt's Sufferings and Satisfaction is ours, or in our place, or ſtead, only in regard to the Effects: But if he ſuffered and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in our place or ſtead (or his Satisfaction be ours) any more, or otherwiſe than as to the Effects, I perceive than neither his Brethren on one ſide, nor I on the other, can ſee by what diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, unleſs by words only, without the thing that makes the difference (when theſe Diſtinctions without a Difference do ſtill quite ſpoil all) he can evade us, but that he muſt come over quite to me, or them, let him chooſe which. Believe it, Chriſt <hi>died in our ſtead,</hi> is by Interpretation only, the <hi>Believer Unpuniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Mr. <hi>W.</hi> offers upon this account in his <hi>Man made Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> p. 76 to 83. I have conſidered, and it is but an honeſt thing to give a Man his weight. Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is double he counts, either his Performance of the <hi>Mediatorial Covenant;</hi> or his <hi>Right to the Reward</hi> being performed. The one is a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in relation to the <hi>Precept,</hi> the other in relation to the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miant
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94662:18"/>Sanction.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> Righteouſneſs is imputed to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever (he ſays) <hi>Mediately,</hi> which is, I think, but the ſame I ſay, it is imputed only in regard to the Effects. This is the Simile he uſes, and the Explication makes good. God looks on what Chriſt did and ſuffered (he urges) as done <hi>for us,</hi> and therefore what he did and ſuffered is <hi>ours</hi> as to the <hi>Benefits:</hi> But God does not look on what Chriſt did and ſuffered as <hi>done by us,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what he did and ſuffered is <hi>ours</hi> no otherwiſe. The <hi>latter,</hi> Righteouſneſs then he ſays is imputed to Believers <hi>Immediately,</hi> which he explains thus. A part of that Reward Chriſt hath a Right to, is to have a Seed, that they ſhall believe and be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. Now Believers have this Right, which Chriſt hath, that they ſhall be pardoned, <hi>It is made theirs; They have not only the Benefits, but are inveſted in Chriſt's Right to thoſe Benefits; They have not only a Right to Pardon, but have Chriſt's Right to that Pardon.</hi> This he ſays, but how can this be? Chriſt's Right to his Reward is as properly his own Righteouſneſs, and inherent in him, as his Righteouſneſs of Obedience. Both are Accidents in him as their Subject. One of them, the Righteouſneſs of his Obedience, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be <hi>ours in it ſelf,</hi> becauſe Accidents do not <hi>Migrare à ſubjecto in ſubjectum,</hi> and how can Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſay ſo of this? If he does not make this <hi>Right of Chriſt</hi> to be ours <hi>in ſe,</hi> it is as good as to ſay nothing. And when the <hi>Obedience</hi> of Chriſt is not <hi>in ſe</hi> ours but by <hi>Imputation,</hi> and that only in the <hi>Effects,</hi> how the <hi>Right to the Reward,</hi> which is Chriſt's Right, can be <hi>ſo ours,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this <hi>Migration</hi> (which is impoſſible,) I am yet to conſider, and digeſt not. We cannot be made <hi>inherently</hi> Righteous by his Righteouſneſs, and how ſhall we be <hi>ſo</hi> enrighted by his Right? But after this, If Chriſt's Right it ſelf (or his Right <hi>in ſe</hi>) be not the Believers, but only the <hi>virtue</hi> of it, then is there here a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web ſpun finely, when all comes but to an <hi>Imputation</hi> of this <hi>Right,</hi> as well as of his <hi>Obedience,</hi> as to the Effects only. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, either then there is nothing at all in this, or if there be ſomething, ſo as he may come off in his ſaying, that <hi>Beſides the Effects, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed,</hi> it is a coming off but with a Fallacy (<hi>fallacia dictionis:</hi>) For he underſtands that Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is ſo called in relation to the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> and we ſpeak altogether of his Righteouſneſs in relation to the <hi>Precept</hi> of the Law of Redemption.</p>
               <p>I muſt yet add, If Mr. <hi>W.</hi> will ſtand to it, that the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt (without equivocating) is imputed to us
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94662:19"/>
                  <hi>beſides</hi> (or any more than in regard to) the <hi>Effects,</hi> then let him ſay, that Chriſt obeyed and ſuffered not only <hi>for us,</hi> or <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> but alſo <hi>in our Perſons,</hi> taking it too in their own ſenſe, and ſo make a full end with his Brethren. But I argue, If Chriſt obeyed and ſuffered ſo <hi>in our Perſons,</hi> as well as <hi>for us,</hi> and <hi>in our ſtead;</hi> Then ſhould not we obey at all; Then ſhould not we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at all; for he that hath perfectly obeyed, can be puniſhed for nothing; Then ſhould we need no Forgiveneſs; Then would Chriſt's Sufferings for us having obeyed be needleſs; Then muſt he be lookt on by God as the Sinner; Then muſt the <hi>Culpa</hi> as well as the <hi>Poena</hi> be imputed to him; Then could not Chriſt be our Mediator, becauſe he is the Offending Party, and a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator is a third Party between the Offender and the Offended; in which Perſon he obeyed and ſuffered for us. Then laſtly ſhould Impunity and Life be due to us immediately by a meer Reſultancy from his Obedience and Sufferings, and not be given by the Interpoſition of a new Law or Covenant upon terms as they are according to the Goſpel, which is ſubverted therefore by that Opinion. Once more, If Chriſt ſuffered in our Perſons, then ſhould he have borne the <hi>ſame</hi> Sufferings, and if they were the <hi>ſame,</hi> they could not be <hi>inſtead</hi> of <hi>Ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſay the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt in it ſelf is <hi>imputed</hi> to us, though it be not <hi>Ours,</hi> only in the <hi>Effects:</hi> But Mr. <hi>W.</hi> muſt not come off ſo, for I ſay, To be imputed in it ſelf, is to be Ours by Imputation, that is, <hi>Judicially Ours,</hi> which draws the ſame Conſequences, as <hi>Ours in it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I pray let us conſider a little in good earneſt, what is in this Conception of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> that <hi>beſides the Effects being made Ours, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed;</hi> Is there any thing in it, or nothing in it? Is it of <hi>any</hi> or <hi>no</hi> Signification? Certainly if his meaning comes not to thus much, that beſides the Effects, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs it ſelf is <hi>ours</hi> alſo by <hi>Imputation,</hi> it is an idle, impertinent, vile Trifling with us (which in regard to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> is not to be ſpoken without ſome Reſentment) in ſo exquiſite a matter: If he will grant his meaning to be thus much, that though Chriſt's Righteouſneſs cannot be inherently Ours, yet it is indeed <hi>Ours by Imputation,</hi> then is he come quite home to his Brethren, who never ſaid, or intended any other.</p>
               <p>After this I argue, If Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be imputed to us in it ſelf, Then were it <hi>pleadable</hi> by us, as if <hi>we our ſelves had done and ſuffered what Chriſt did,</hi> which Mr. <hi>W.</hi> does in effect allow,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94662:19"/>or without Tergiverſation muſt, <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> p. 39, 40. And alſo, Then muſt God have dealt with us, as <hi>if we had;</hi> which he does more poſitively allow, P. 42. <hi>To impute to one</hi> (ſays he) <hi>what is ſuffered by another, is to deal with him as if he himſelf had ſuffered.</hi> But God hath not dealt thus with us; and we cannot plead ſo with him, which appear by the ſaid Conſequences. It is not all one as if we had done and ſuffered in Chriſt, what he did and ſuffered for us, for <hi>Satisfaction</hi> is another thing than this. It is not all one in other reſpects; it is as good for us only in the <hi>obtained</hi> (when attained) <hi>Effects.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>PART IV.</head>
               <p>THERE remains now one thing, and a chief thing, yet to be done, which is, to offer ſomething that may ſerve to reconcile ſuch Brethren at leaſt as agree in the main, though it cannot ſuch as quite differ in the Point. I ſhall firſt dilate a little more for lights ſake, and ſo be lead thereto by the matter it ſelf. Chriſt in Scripture is ſaid to dye <hi>for us,</hi> and to dye <hi>for our Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For our Sins</hi> he may be ſaid to dye or ſuffer in theſe two ſenſes. <hi>For our Sins,</hi> To expiate them, to deliver us from them, the Guilt and Condemnation due to us for them: <hi>For our Sins,</hi> As the Meritorious Cauſe of his Death and Sufferings, upon his voluntary undertaking that Expiation. Both theſe Senſes are good, and to be retained.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For us</hi> may have a double Senſe alſo, <hi>Loco noſtro;</hi> or <hi>Bono noſtro.</hi> In our <hi>ſtead;</hi> or in regard to our <hi>Benefit.</hi> The <hi>Socinians</hi> will have Chriſt to dye for us only <hi>bono noſtro,</hi> which they fetch about too, ſo as makes his dying for us of no more concern than a Martyr's. Chriſt by his Death confirmed his Doctrine: This makes us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it: His Doctrine teaches a Holy Life: By a Holy Life we leave Sin. Chriſt therefore dyed for our Sins. But we hold Chriſt dyed <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> in our <hi>ſtead,</hi> in our <hi>room.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, <hi>In our ſtead,</hi> or <hi>loco noſtro,</hi> may have again a double Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In our stead,</hi> As repreſenting our Perſons, ſo that God looks on us as having done and ſuffered what Chriſt did and ſuffered for us. As what my Attorney or Delegate does for me, I am accounted to have done. He is the Agent <hi>Naturally,</hi> but <hi>Civilly</hi> or <hi>Legally</hi> it is <hi>I:</hi> In this Interpretation we are not to hold Chriſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94662:20"/>dyed in our ſtead, for that draws all thoſe mentioned Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences after it, which muſt carefully be avoided.</p>
               <p>There is another Interpretation then of Suffering in our ſtead. <hi>In our stead,</hi> that is, To ſave us from Suffering our ſelves; and this is the Senſe we are firſt to know to be the right, and then ſtand by it. To do any thing or ſuffer it in the room of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have ſaid, is to do or ſuffer that thing that the other may eſcape it, and in this right ſenſe it is, that <hi>Grotius</hi> underſtands Chriſt's dying <hi>for us,</hi> and ſpeaks of a <hi>Commutation</hi> or <hi>Subrogation</hi> of Chriſt's Perſon in the room of <hi>ours</hi> in his Sufferings for us, as the Beaſt was ſubrogated in the place of him that Sacrificed it. If any ſtretch ſuch words of his farther than ſo, they abuſe both their Underſtanding and him.</p>
               <p>Now when this <hi>In our ſtead,</hi> in uſual ſpeaking, is Suffering or doing <hi>in our Perſon,</hi> I am brought at laſt to a pauſe, as to the words we uſe, That Chriſt ſuffered and obeyed <hi>in our Perſons,</hi> is ſaid by our Divines without ſcruple, and Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> does but handſomly expreſs what they ſpeak ordinarily. Nay Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does acknowledge that theſe words may be uſed, if we put a right Senſe on them. And what is that Senſe? The Senſe that muſt be put on them, if right, is indeed to confound theſe two things, which I, and Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> too, do ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſtinguiſh otherwiſe, that is, Chriſt's Suffering <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> and <hi>in our Perſons.</hi> Let theſe two Expreſſions then be underſtood as one and the ſame thing, and either of them may be uſed. If the ſaying Chriſt ſuffered in our Perſons, as Chriſt ſuffered in our ſtead, be taken in the <hi>firſt</hi> ſenſe of <hi>In our stead,</hi> ſo as to draw on theſe Conſequences, I ſay we muſt deny that he ſuffered in our Perſons, or dyed in our ſtead, the Saying is <hi>Antinomian:</hi> But if it be made to ſignifie no more than Suffering in our ſtead, in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Interpretation of <hi>In our ſtead,</hi> that is, ſo as not to draw thoſe Conſequences, the Saying is <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and we may allow it. Thus much is ſafe and ſure, from whence it appears, that ſome Diſtinction here in other words, the members whereof (<hi>Membra dividentia ſunt contraria</hi>) being made ſuch as all theſe ſaid Conſequences may be attributed to one of them, and none of them to the other, ſo that we could ſimply, only by granting the one Branch, and denying the other, reconcile in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, might do better. Suppoſe then I ſhould recall thoſe words, a little above where I count (or hitherto have) <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Suffering and Obeying in <hi>our Perſons,</hi> and <hi>our</hi> Obeying and Suffering in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94662:20"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt's Perſon</hi> to be all one; and inſtead of diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, <hi>in our Stead,</hi> and <hi>in our Perſons,</hi> make <hi>theſe</hi> to be two things, I ſay, make <hi>this</hi> the Diſtinction upon which to ſet all right, by ſaying that Chriſt obeyed and ſuffered <hi>in our Perſons,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding only <hi>in our stead in the right ſenſe declared,</hi> but denying that we ſuffered and obeyed <hi>in his Perſon, or that God does look on us as legally to have obeyed and ſatisfied in him,</hi> becauſe of thoſe Conſequences (I ſay ſtill) before mentioned, which if propoſed by way of Argument againſt it, none can anſwer. (Let Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> try, and if he cannot, Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> muſt not in Modeſty think he can,) Would not this do our work?</p>
               <p>I crave here Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Attention, becauſe in a Diſcourſe I had laſt with him, he diſtinguiſhed thus. He held he ſaid a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of <hi>Perſon,</hi> but not of <hi>Perſons.</hi> I ask'd him if he had read the Diſtinction in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and if he had his Author I ſhould like it well. We know the Scripture ſays, Chriſt <hi>dyed for us,</hi> and obeyed <hi>for us,</hi> and that is we ſay in our room, in our ſtead. It no where ſays, we ſinned in his ſtead, our Sins were not <hi>for him,</hi> though he bare them. He ſuffered and obeyed in our <hi>Perſon as in our stead,</hi> I have ſaid, there is a Commutation of <hi>Perſon;</hi> but we ſuffered not, and obeyed not in <hi>his Perſon</hi> (ſeeing theſe Conſequences aforeſaid follow upon that,) ſo there is not of <hi>Perſons.</hi> And what if Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and I ſhould have fallen here into the ſame Conception? Nay, what if Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> whoſe Book is cited againſt Mr. <hi>W.</hi> ſhould have been ſo profoundly careful of his words, that though he hath ſo amply owned the <hi>Sinner</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as his Surety) to be <hi>one</hi> in Law, <hi>Judicially one,</hi> as to the paying our Debts, or bearing our Puniſhment, or in doing and ſuffering what we ought to have done and ſuffered, hath yet never expreſs'd them <hi>One ſo,</hi> as that God accounts us to have <hi>obeyed and ſuffered in him?</hi> I cannot ſay it, but if he hath, then are we very lucky in this: And why may we not agree thus (as I ſay) with that worthy and beloved Man? Chriſt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Our</hi> Subſtitute, but we not <hi>Christ's:</hi> He obeyed and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in <hi>our Perſon,</hi> but not we in <hi>His;</hi> and if we did not obey and ſuffer in <hi>his Perſon,</hi> then muſt not his Righteouſneſs be <hi>Ours</hi> neither, but in the <hi>Effects.</hi> Let the Doctor chooſe here whether he will cleave to his old Friend Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> or his new Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and let Mr. <hi>W.</hi> conſider himſelf who is likelieſt to have ſeen deeper, he or Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> into the Bowels of this Point. This I ſtand upon, God looks not on us as the Performers of what
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94662:21"/>Chriſt performed in our behalf; and in our behalf, in our ſtead, or room, to ſuffer, I have ſaid, and ſaid, is to ſuffer that <hi>We</hi> might not ſuffer. To ſay then that Chriſt's Suffering is <hi>Ours</hi> (or accounted Ours) is to forget what Suffering <hi>in anothers room</hi> does mean. If Chriſt ſuffered and obeyed (I preſs it) in our ſtead, place, room, that we might not ſuffer and obey (in the ſenſe in due place explained) then did not, then could not he ſuffer and obey ſo, as that God ſhould look on us as if we have <hi>ſuffered and obeyed in him.</hi> This is a Contradiction, and he that ſays Chriſt's Righteouſneſs it ſelf is <hi>imputed</hi> to us as <hi>ours,</hi> is involved in it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> argues, <hi>If Chriſt paid the Law Debt of Satisfaction, which the Elect in their Perſons ſhould have paid, and thereby freed them from the ſame, he ſuſtained the Perſon of the Elect</hi> (or our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) <hi>in his Sufferings,</hi> Co. Op. 251. I anſwer, We will grant to him here the uſe of ſuch words, Chriſt <hi>ſuſtained our Perſon,</hi> or <hi>ſuffered in our Perſons</hi> in this ſenſe quoted, that through Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction given by him to the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> Elect Believers are freed from ſatisfying the <hi>Law</hi> themſelves (the Language thus pruned, for the Law was not executed, or <hi>Law-Debt</hi> paid, but <hi>Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> given to ſave its Execution on the Debtor:) But when he confounds the Uſe with the other Senſe alſo as one, that in Chriſt's <hi>ſuſtaining our Perſon,</hi> God does account us to have ſuffered and ſatisfied in his, he is fallen into this Inconſiſtency, that neither <hi>Rutherford</hi> nor <hi>Bates</hi> (I doubt,) nor <hi>Williams</hi> himſelf, hath <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently</hi> obſerved. What is done in our ſtead, or in our Perſon, in the one Senſe, cannot be ſo in the other. If God (I muſt ſay it again) will have Chriſt to <hi>ſuſtain our Perſons</hi> in his Sufferings, that we might not Suffer, then muſt we not alſo <hi>ſuſtain His,</hi> as that God ſhould account us to have ſuffered. This is the Inconſiſtency, and the Reader muſt pardon me the forced Repetition.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi> (who I ſay is included here) does tell us, (<hi>Man made Righteous,</hi> p. 62, 63.) <hi>That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Condition of the Reward, was a Faederal Righteouſneſs, above what was to be Mans Righteouſneſs by the Law of Works,</hi> which he exemplifies in ſeveral Inſtances. I argue againſt him hereupon, <hi>Therefore</hi> the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt <hi>it ſelf</hi> cannot be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us, but is imputed to us in the <hi>Effects.</hi> It was in our ſtead, therefore not ours <hi>in it ſelf:</hi> It was in our ſtead, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ours <hi>in the Benefit</hi> of it, and in the Benefit only.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94662:21"/>
               <p>Thus much for Mr. <hi>W.</hi> with whom I am concerned, becauſe we being ſo near of Opinion, I would have that Satisfaction from him, as to take theſe Matters between us into his ſecond Thoughts, and to conſider what I offer, ſo as if there be light, or right Notion in it, he may make it more clear by the fulneſs of his Expreſſion (when mine is barren,) and indeed tell what Dr. <hi>Bates ſhould</hi> mean, and what I <hi>do</hi> mean, better perhaps than my ſelf. I do conjure him, ſo far as he is convinced, not to be aſhamed to own the Truth, however naked it be here, and without Friends: Or elſe to give me ſufficient reaſon for my return to his Temper, which ſeems to me ſuch, as to let his Opinion be that, or no other but that, which he can ſo defend againſt his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, as to loſe no Repute with his Followers.</p>
               <p>For Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> I am not concerned, for whether I differ with him in all, or not at all, we leave one another to our own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is the words of others he hath quoted, and I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend himſelf free to his own Opinion, wherein I know he hath had, and may have, Candour and Latitude; which may be therefore the ſame with mine, as theirs, if he will, and if he will not, he may chooſe. He is one that for his Induſtry in reading Books, and good Temper upon it I do value; and though there be ſome that are ſtumbled, at the Intereſt he had in King <hi>James</hi>'s Court, I judge, that ſeeing it was laid out mainly to get and maintain their Liberty, the Brethren have little reaſon to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and much leſs to envy it. Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> (I muſt tell ſome) had no Gift from that King. King <hi>James</hi> indeed knew how to toul Men into him by Liberty of Conſcience, and make that a Schoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Horn to have drawn Popery upon the Nation, if he had not been prevented: But any one may eaſily believe, he never had ſuch a Heart to any Nonconformiſt Proteſtant, as to <hi>build us a Synagogue.</hi> I had written about a ſide upon this account, but blotting out the reſt, I will let thus much ſtand, that upon this Intereſt of Mr. <hi>Lobb,</hi> I had Admittance once into King <hi>James</hi>'s Preſence, and having ſpoken what I came about, and ſomething concerning his Diſpenſing with the Law, I ſaid thus to him, That <hi>if he would maintain that Diſpenſing Power, which I counted he then exerciſed, he changed his Government, and the People would fight with him, and their Cauſe be good.</hi> I ſpake it in ſuch words, and ſome the ſame (as Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> can witneſs) that are in the enſuing Paper, which I printed lately by it ſelf for ſerving the preſent Generation, according to my Mite; but knowing how ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94662:22"/>ſingle Papers are uſed, torn, burnt, loſt, and having at firſt wrote it in theſe Sheets, I did not intend but it ſhould alſo come out with them: In a Book it will be kept, and I Prognoſticate too, will remain, to that Age to come, wherein no Man will be found, that dare write or ſay the ſame. That Doctrine was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time, which in King <hi>Charles</hi> and King <hi>James</hi>'s was made Treaſon, and now in King <hi>William</hi>'s hath been Juſtified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Memoriae Sacrum.</head>
               <p>WHereas there have been ſome that fear God, of all Ranks, the higher and meaner Rank and Conditions, Clergy and Laity, that could not ſubmit to the Preſent Government, ſo as to take the Oath of Fidelity to the King, nay nor ſo much as come to the Liturgy (whereof otherwiſe they were ſo fond) becauſe of the Prayers that are there ſaid for him: And whereas there are now many more, that though they have Sworn Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to <hi>William</hi> as King <hi>de Facto,</hi> they cannot come to an Acknowledgment of him as King <hi>de Jure,</hi> ſo as to <hi>Aſſociate</hi> in a Cordial Defence of him with others; All which Doubts depend upon the ſole Queſtion about King <hi>James</hi>'s Conſcionable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; wherein it is not meerly out of Intereſt, (as moſt ſelfiſh Men will think) Humour, or Inclination, that they are gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd, but out of Conſcience grounded on the <hi>Thirteenth to the Romans:</hi> And foraſmuch as I wrote a Book in the year 1680. printed for <hi>R. Clavel,</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Peaceable Reſolution of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, touching our preſent Impoſitions,</hi> wherein I have ſpoken for Loyalty againſt Reſiſtance, not only as much, (for it is a Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Book) but more in one Vertical Point than others, and too much upon further Knowledge than is fit for our Engliſh Government: I do think meet, for the rectifying my ſelf, and an humble Tender for other Satisfaction, (eſpecially ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Loyaliſts as have forſaken what they had, rather than the Confeſſion they once made in ſo ſolemn a <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,</hi> which was then enjoyned all Conformiſts, That it is <hi>not Lawful to take Arms againſt the King upon any Pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi>) to bear this Teſtimony to that Text of the Apoſtle, and leave it on Record before I dye, being now 75 years Old, for the ſake of Poſterity. The words are theſe, <hi>Let every Soul be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94662:22"/>ſubject unto the Higher Powers: For there is no Power but of God. The Powers that be, ore Ordained of God. Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two Diſtinctions here neceſſary to be known; To offer more, were to Confound, not Edifie. One is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> It is Dr. <hi>Field</hi>'s Diſtinction in the <hi>Words,</hi> and in the <hi>Meaning</hi> none of thoſe that are for the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience,</hi> but will ſo far agree with us. We are not always to <hi>Obey</hi> the Higher Powers (Themſelves muſt acknowledge) but we are (they ſay) always to be in <hi>Subjection,</hi> and never <hi>Reſiſt,</hi> riſe up, and deliver our ſelves from them. If God forbids what the Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or if God commands what he forbids, God muſt be obey'd rather than Man. This by their Word <hi>[Paſſive]</hi> they aſſent unto; but, as to the Point of <hi>Subjection,</hi> it is in that, the Queſtion and Difference lyes betwen us. The other Diſtinction then is, what They have not yet known, nor was it ever yet uſed before by any that I know, unleſs perhaps my ſelf. The <hi>Senſe</hi> almoſt all have, but not the <hi>Elucidation.</hi> Diſtinguiſh we then between theſe two things, which certainly are different things, the Powers <hi>that are,</hi> and the Powers that <hi>are</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">There may be a <hi>Pretended Power,</hi> where there is None: Such as was King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> and his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions</hi> now.</note> 
                  <hi>not.</hi> This is a plain Diſtinction, every one can underſtand it, and it is undeniable. The Powers, the Higher Powers in the Text are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Powers that be.</hi> This is certain and expreſs, <hi>the Powers that be,</hi> are the Powers in the Text, the Powers that are of God, the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation. Let this be granted to theſe Devout Men; but then muſt they grant to me again what cannot be denied by any, that as for the Powers <hi>that are not,</hi> the Powers (I ſay) that are not <hi>the Powers that be,</hi> they are not the Powers in the Text, not the Powers that are of God, not the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt <hi>them,</hi> (and not the Powers <hi>that be</hi>) ſhall not receive to themſelves Damnation. This is is plain and undeniable as before.</p>
               <p>Now there is one Queſtion to be ask'd, which alone will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the whole Caſe at ſtake between us, and that is this: What is the true Meaning of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? What is really
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94662:23"/>and in good earneſt (ſo as the Conſcience may reſt upon it,) <hi>That,</hi> which is meant by <hi>the Powers that be?</hi> I Anſwer, <hi>The Powers that be,</hi> are certainly the Powers according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent known<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtus</hi> brought in a New <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> into the Roman Government, the People conſenting: And <hi>Nero</hi> was Obeyed, and not to be <hi>Reſiſted,</hi> as ſuppoſedly Ruling thereby.</note> Conſtitution. There are Higher Powers (or Kings) whoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is Abſolute, and ſo Abſolute, as that Subjects have no Liberty of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or Propriety in Goods by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: But it is not ſo with other Higher Powers (or Kings) whoſe Government is according to a ſuppoſed Original Contract (appearing in the Laws) which gives the People ſuch <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Rights,</hi> as the King ſuch a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative,</hi> extending ſo far, and no farther than the Contract allows. There is here therefore two things to be conſidered, the <hi>Poteſtas,</hi> and <hi>Forma Regiminis;</hi> the Power and the Form in ſuch Governments. The Form or Conſtitution (which tells what ſort of Government it ſhall be, what Perſons ſhall Govern, and how far they may go) is of Men, (of Men altoge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in the <hi>Jews</hi> Commonwealth) and then the Power does flow from GOD to Rule ſo, and no otherwiſe, but according to that Conſtitution. <hi>Poteſtas eſt à Deo,</hi> but <hi>Forma ab Hominibus,</hi> ſays Biſhop <hi>Andrews.</hi> If then the Higher Powers for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration Rule not by that Form, or according to that Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, (but deſignedly and reſolvedly, and not by a ſlip and meer Inadvertency, depart from it,) the Power <hi>à Deo,</hi> the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas,</hi> fails them; and they do <hi>Cadere de Jure,</hi> fall from their Right to our Subjection.<note n="*" place="margin">A Diſpenſing Power indefinitely maintain'd, is a Power over the Laws. A Power over the Laws, ſubverts the Government. A Change of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Abſolves the Subject from his Allegiance.</note> I have thought on this long, I was at <hi>Oxford</hi> when I compoſed that Book forementioned, and had the Uſe of the Library, and I pitch'd on this as the Texts Fundamental Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, That <hi>the Powers that be,</hi> are the <hi>Government</hi> in every Country according to its own <hi>Conſtitution:</hi> And conſequently, that the <hi>Subjection</hi> (or Non-Reſiſtance) which is required of God as due to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> is a Subjection (or Non-Reſiſtance) no other but according to the ſame. Look you Sirs, the Scripture does not go to preſcribe, alter, or meddle with the Governments of the Nations, but it ſuppoſes a Government in every Kingdom or Country, and commands Subjection to the Government <hi>that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94662:23"/>is.</hi> We overturn all if we Preach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than thus, <hi>Evangelium non abolet Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litias.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">When <hi>Luther</hi> had taught that the Magiſtrate ſhould not be Reſiſted, and ſome Lawyers prov'd to him, that the <hi>German Empire</hi> was not Abſolute, but that the Laws thereof permitted Reſiſtance, he then held they might make a League to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves; Upon this Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the Goſpel aboliſhes not the Laws of any Commonwealth,</hi> Sleidan lib. 8. Note here in the way, That if <hi>William</hi> be <hi>Lawful King,</hi> King by <hi>Law,</hi> then he muſt be <hi>Rightful King</hi> [King <hi>in Foro Interiori,</hi> unto whom Subjection is due, not for <hi>Wrath,</hi> but <hi>Conſcience-ſake;</hi> King <hi>in foro Dei Sive Conſcientiae,</hi> and not <hi>in foro Exteriori Sive Humano</hi> only:] Upon the ſame Reaſon, Becauſe the Goſpel, the Word or Laws of God does <hi>ſupponere,</hi> not <hi>ponere</hi> any thing in this Matter, but according to the Law of the Land.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now then let us come to the Government of our Nation, and this Government we all know (and none more like than theſe Men to ſtand by it) is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> the Secretary of State in two Reigns, hath told us in his Authentick Book, <hi>De Republica Anglicana:</hi> That is, <hi>A Government regulated by Laws,</hi> a Government which is <hi>Kingly</hi> by the Statutes of the Realm, and not at the <hi>Will of the Lord. Non eſt Rex ubi Voluntas imperat, non Lex,</hi> ſays <hi>Bracton;</hi> and ſo ſay all our Great Lawyers. Well! Such being the Conſtitution of our Government, Be it Known and Acknowledged, That if any King of <hi>England</hi> therefore ſhall Rule ſo (or really go about it ſo, that if he be not hindred, he will effect it) as to change the Government, or <hi>Manner of the Kingdom</hi> (as the Scripture expreſſes it) from <hi>Legal</hi> to <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> from <hi>Regal</hi> to <hi>Deſpotical;</hi> and it ſhall pleaſe God to give the People, who are Free Subjects, the Happy Means of a Deliverance, they do not reſiſt in this Caſe, or riſe up againſt the <hi>Powers that be,</hi> the Powers in the Text, the Powers that are of GOD, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of GOD: But the Powers <hi>not</hi> in the Text, the Powers that are <hi>not</hi> of GOD, the Powers that are <hi>not</hi> the Ordinance of God, and it being indeed only a Riſing <hi>for</hi> the Government, and not <hi>againſt</hi> the Government, and no reſiſting <hi>the Powers that be,</hi> they ſhall not receive to themſelves Damnation. This is the Caſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>As We know,</hi> (ſays <hi>Hooker</hi> in larger Words) <hi>That they are Lords of ſuch or ſuch Lands, unto whom, in defect of Heirs, they fall by Eſcheat: So does it rightly follow, ſeeing Dominion, when there is none to inherit it,</hi> (or when it is forfeited) <hi>returns to the Body, that it does fundamentally and radically reſide in the Body, and that the Inheritors hold it in dependency on them.</hi> This Saying of his, I confeſs in my Judgment, does require that grain of Salt, which is above in the Paper (too much to be explained and adapted to a Marginal Note:) But is ſo far true to me, as undoubtedly to make the Application. Our Government therefore thus Eſcheating, or become Forfeit to the People, and they by their Repreſentatives in a <hi>Convention,</hi> having ſettled it on <hi>William,</hi> here is the moſt certain, true, indubitable Title that any Prince is capable of; and better than any other hath to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for ought I know, in the Earth beſides.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:94662:24"/>
               <p>There are two Reaſons now (beſides the Conſcience to my ſelf in regard to the Book forecited) for the <hi>Publication;</hi> which being apparent, I own. The <hi>One,</hi> That all Honeſt Scrupulous Men, who have been hitherto <hi>Non-Jurors</hi> upon the Point of Conſcience (as to them) may be <hi>ſo</hi> ſatisfied to take the Oath of Fidelity to King <hi>William</hi> (with us that have,) <hi>as</hi> to bleſs God for him, and to enter the Aſſociation, as they ſee it good for them. The <hi>Other,</hi> That the King himſelf, and thoſe that ſucceed him in the Throne, may not be tempted by the Love of their People, or Liberality of Parliaments, to make ſuch Uſe of their Raiſed Strength, as our Neighbour Kings have done, to go out of the Circle of our <hi>Engliſh Conſtitution:</hi> Eſpecially knowing, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Nation, and the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of it alſo is hereby ſo reſolved, that under King <hi>James</hi> we would not be <hi>Papiſts;</hi> under thoſe that ſucceed, We will not be <hi>Slaves.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Having ſaid this for the <hi>People,</hi> I muſt ſay one thing alſo for the <hi>King</hi> out of the ſame Principle. There is the <hi>Poſitive</hi> and <hi>Negative Power</hi> of Rulers. According to our <hi>Engliſh Government</hi> it is true, and to be held, that the King can <hi>Poſitively</hi> do nothing but according to Law: But it being true alſo, and to be conſidered, that the <hi>Supreme Law</hi> in all Polities is the <hi>Common Good;</hi> if a Prince, in the uſe of his Power only, which is <hi>Negative,</hi> ſhould upon occaſion do ſomething otherwiſe than Law, for the Benefit of the Subject <hi>(Bona fide)</hi> and not his private Ends, I do believe, both Politically, and as a Divine, that he may have a good Conſcience in it; and when he has, that he is not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he acts then <hi>againſt</hi> the Law, but <hi>according</hi> to it, ſeeing he does <hi>Govern</hi> in ſuch a Caſe by the <hi>Supreme Law,</hi> unto which all others are Subordinate. Not long before King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Death, the <hi>Juſtices</hi> were ſending Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to Priſon for <hi>Conventicling,</hi> but he hearing of it, and being told it might kill the <hi>ill</hi> good Man, out of his kind Nature, ſends word immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately he would have him forborne. To have controul'd the Law to a Man's hurt, it had been Tyranny; but when it was only for Good, without detriment to any, who could open his Mouth againſt it? It is to be ſuppoſed no Law-givers can foreſee all Caſes that may happen, and when Equity and a good Conſcience is againſt the Letter of the Law, thus much I think Juſtifiable by the Old Covenant Oath, where the King Sware to execute the Laws, <hi>Cum Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia &amp; Miſerecordia:</hi> If not it will be, by that Power our Kings have of granting <hi>a Nolle Profequi</hi> in ſome caſes to Offenders, and much more by that of Pardoning All <hi>ad libitum,</hi> which a <hi>Majore ad Minus</hi> cannot but warrant more than this. It is fit that Kings, before they Swear, do underſtand their Oath to have this Conſtruction, and to know that which is much more to the purpoſe, that any Law which is againſt God or Nature, that is, which is againſt the Law of Nature, or Word of God, or the Common Good, is really <hi>in foro Conſcientiae,</hi> No Law; ſo that in the Non-Proſecution thereof, they are not to be condemned. Nay, if a Prince by Malverſation, even <hi>Poſitive</hi> or <hi>Privative,</hi> ſhall render himſelf Obnoxious to God, and the People, it is good yet for the Subject to bear with him (as we do with Storms) ſo long as we can; but if the Caſe comes to that once, as the Nation is in danger of <hi>Ruin</hi> by it, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Non-reſiſtance, any longer than we can help our ſelves, is perfect Ignorance of our <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>raving</hi> Obſtinacy. <hi>Salus Populi Suprema lex eſto.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <closer>Habetüs Sententiam meam, in Cauſa hac gravissima.
<signed>J. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:94662:24"/>
               <head>The Poſtſcript to the Reader.</head>
               <p>THERE are ſeveral Pieces, that at ſeveral Times, upon ſeveral Subjects, I have written, called, <hi>The Middle Way.</hi> One is the <hi>Middle Way of Juſtification,</hi> which I printed in the year 71 or 72, and reprinted lately 95, upon the account of our Brethrens Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about that Point. In that ſecond Edition I have gathered up all Paſſages that concern that Subject, out of the reſt of thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to put them to it, and took advantage from certain <hi>Exceptions</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> to add ſomething that I thought wanting in a ſingle Sheet, and have here ſupplied what was yet in my Mind to ſay farther upon this Occaſion. Now if the Reader ſhall bid the Bookſeller ſtitch theſe ſix Sheets, that <hi>one Sheet</hi> (ſo called) and thoſe eight or nine together, and then ſhall <hi>take time</hi> to read them, and <hi>notice</hi> of what he reads (unleſs he thinks this Point of <hi>Juſtification</hi> be ſuch, as is not worthy his Time or Thoughts, which was an <hi>Article</hi> of ſo great Concern to our firſt Reformers,) and does not meet with ſomething or other in them (and that as an <hi>Original</hi>) which may ſerve at leaſt <hi>Vice cotis</hi> to whet his own Underſtanding upon them, then is it not <hi>I</hi> my ſelf only, but <hi>two</hi> of our moſt eminent Brethren while alive (as appears by their hands put to one of my <hi>Papers</hi>) are deceived. I will add, that if Mr. <hi>W.</hi> therefore ſhall not now ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to peruſe them, and finding any ſuch Matter which he can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, or make out better for me than I have done, if he does it not, then am I farther diſappointed in one End of this preſent Work, as alſo of my believed Eſtimation of Mr. <hi>Williams. For according to what a Man's Mind is moſt upon in ſuch Diſputes as theſe, the Inveſtigation of Truth, or the Defence of ones ſelf, ſuch is his value more or leſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having yet room, the fear of the want whereof made me put thoſe two Paragraphs (p. 29.) into a Marginal Note, that ſhould elſe have been part of the Book, I will uſe it to ſupply one thing lacking in the ſingle Sheet mentioned. The Sacrifice and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt's Death and Life, is that which hath procured Pardon and Salvation to every Believing Sinner, upon the account of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction God as Rector hath received by it; ſo that being Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator alſo (and above Law) he might with Demonſtration too of his Righteouſneſs (relax, and hath relaxed or diſpenſed with) his Law of Works, requiring another Condition to thoſe Benefits in a new one, the Law of Grace, or the Goſpel. This Pardon now and Life (or Grant thereof) upon Condition, being the Grand
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94662:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fruits of our Redemption, it is a Queſtion between Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and I, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Condition it ſelf alſo be a Fruit of Chriſt's Purchaſe, which if it be not, derives not yet from our Free Will, but the Grace of Election. It is not agreeable to my Genius to make Chriſt's Redemption, which I would have One thing and Univerſal, to be differently inſluxive on the <hi>Elect</hi> and others. I have opened this Apprehenſion of mine in that ſingle Sheet men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and there are two Conſiderations moreover offered againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Opinion, which I deſire Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to weigh Honeſtly, and, if he can, to ſolve me the Difficulty; or if he cannot, to come with me to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. The Lord Chriſt; by Redeeming the World and conſequently by his Death, hath obtained a Right of Dominion over it, and by that Right does give that Condition to whom he will, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. But though Faith therefore and Repentance, in this remote way about, may be ſaid to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Chriſt's Death (as he hath obtained thereby a Power or Right of giving it,) I deny it to be the <hi>immediate Purchaſe,</hi> or <hi>direct Fruit</hi> of it. I deny that Faith is a Fruit of Chriſt's Death, in the ſame manner as Pardon and Life is upon Condition of Faith. I deny that it proceeds from <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> given to God's Juſtice (which Chriſt's Death was) though it may from his Merit, or Redundancy of it, as all other Good does, ſeeing in his Name it is, or through his Merits, that we ask all things at the Hands of God, (as Health, and Wealth, and the like Bleſſings) which we cannot ſay yet Chriſt died that we ſhould have. Again, Chriſt came and died to Save Man, by reſtoring him to Righteouſneſs, from whence he is fallen. Now the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Nature,</hi> we never can be in this Life reſtored to, and there is therefore a Righteouſneſs of <hi>Grace,</hi> which God hath ordained in room of that to Save us, revealed in the Goſpel, and it is called the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> becauſe of this his Ordination. By the Obedience of Chriſt we are ſaid to be <hi>made Righteous,</hi> and <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> or <hi>by the Means of him,</hi> as one has it. But how by the Means of him? Why, by his Death, but this way about ſtill. Chriſt died to procure for us a Covenant with another Condition than that of the Old, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, we become Righteous that never could be ſo elſe; but mark it, when the Condition is purchaſed, the Performance comes not from thence, but from the Free Gift of God. In the mean time, this Mercy that God hath ordained, and doth accept of ſuch a Condition as we do, or can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, muſt not paſs without Reſentment. Bleſſed be the God of Heaven for ſome Senſe and Knowledge of this in theſe Sheets. Bleſſed be God that it is not a Righteouſneſs of the Law required of us, but a Righteouſneſs of the Goſpel. Bleſſed be God it is not by a Righteouſneſs of Works that we are Saved, but a Righteouſneſs, the Failings whereof are pardoned, and the little Done accepted through the alone Merits of Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Which when they had read, they rejoyced for the Conſolation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>Deo Gloria mihi Condonatio. <signed>J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94662:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
